<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God the father glorified: and the worke of mens redemption, and salvation finished by Iesus Christ on earth. Opened in a sermon before the Right Honorable the Lord Major, and the Right Worshipful the sheriffes, aldermen, and recorder, of the Citie of London, the second day of the tenth moneth (called December) 1649. / By Vavasor Powell, a willing (though weake) labourer in Christs Vine-yard in Wales.</title>
            <author>Powell, Vavasor, 1617-1670.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 134 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A90897</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P3087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E584_15</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206284</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865457</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865457</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117698</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A90897)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117698)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 89:E584[15])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God the father glorified: and the worke of mens redemption, and salvation finished by Iesus Christ on earth. Opened in a sermon before the Right Honorable the Lord Major, and the Right Worshipful the sheriffes, aldermen, and recorder, of the Citie of London, the second day of the tenth moneth (called December) 1649. / By Vavasor Powell, a willing (though weake) labourer in Christs Vine-yard in Wales.</title>
                  <author>Powell, Vavasor, 1617-1670.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 62, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Charles Sumptner, for Hannah Allen, at the Crowne in Popes-Head-Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The final leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "Decemb. 11".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:117698:1"/>
            <head>To The Right Honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable, <hi>THOMAS FOOTE,</hi> Lord Major of the famous City of <hi>LONDON:</hi> Together with the Right Worſhipfull, the <hi>Aldermen</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>corder</hi> thereof.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Honourable, and Right Worſhipfull,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N this plaine Sermon (Preached, and publiſhed by your <hi>Call,</hi> and <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand;</hi>) You have preſented unto you the two principalleſt points in all the Scripture, <hi>viz.</hi> The glorifying of God, and the perfecting and finiſhing of that great, and ever-admired worke of mens <hi>Redemption,</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> by Ieſus Chriſt.</p>
            <p>In the former of theſe two, (to wit, in glorifying God) you are to ſtrive to be followers of your Soveraign, and Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour: And in the latter; you are to ſtoope and ſubmit
<pb facs="tcp:117698:2"/>to his <hi>Majeſtie</hi> and <hi>Excellency,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet 1.16. Iſa. 35.2.</note> and to be <hi>humble Seekers,</hi> that you may be <hi>happy ſharers</hi> of this preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous price, and purchaſe. Hee that was a <hi>Soune,</hi> became a <hi>Servant,</hi> and hee that was equall with the higheſt, became inferiour to the loweſt,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.6, 7, 8.</note> that GOD might be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alted, and loſt, undone men, redeemed, and ſaved. The great buſineſſe acted by <hi>CHRIST</hi> in time here below, was contrived,<note place="margin">Zach. 6.13. &amp; 9.11.</note> and agreed upon (betweene GOD and CHRIST) before time in <hi>Heaven</hi> above. If you would ſee all in one, and one in all, then caſt your eyes upon Chriſt,<note place="margin">Col. 3.11. Col. 1.19. Epheſ. 1.10. Col. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>who is all in all, in whom dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth all the fulneſſe of the God-head bodily.</hi> What can you thinke on, ſpeake of, delight in, or deſire to have, but you may finde them in Ieſus Chriſt. If you would know God, as a reconciled God, and as a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, you may know him, and muſt know him, (for there is no other meanes but in &amp; through Ieſus Chriſt. If you would goe to GOD, or have GOD come to you, there is no other way but by him. He is that <hi>Ladder</hi> that <hi>Iacob</hi> ſaw,<note place="margin">Gen. 28.12. with Joh. 1.51.</note> which reached from <hi>Earth</hi> to <hi>Heaven,</hi> upon which the Angels of God <hi>aſcended</hi> and <hi>deſcended.</hi> If you would climbe up this <hi>Ladder,</hi> then muſt you begin in the loweſt ſteps and ſtaves thereof, even in the ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings of this ſweete Saviour. <hi>Chriſt crucified</hi> is the firſt leſſon you muſt learne,<note place="margin">1 Co. 2.2.</note> and that being well learned, it leades by the hand to all the reſt. To ſee your ſinnes laid on Chriſt, and your ſelves virtually in Chriſt, when he ſuffered, (as you were in <hi>Adam</hi> when hee ſinned) is the firſt ſanctified, (and ſoule-ſatisfying) light.</p>
            <p>Nothing humbles, nor melts the heart more, then to ſee the bloudy wounds of this loving Lord: if then you would be <hi>pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitent, oure,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſelf-denying, &amp; weaned from the world,</hi> get a ſight of Christ upon the croſſe, and a feeling of that
<pb facs="tcp:117698:2"/>fellowſhip betweene his perſon, and your perſons in his death. <hi>Meditation</hi> upon the intent of Chriſt in dying, faith to believe the extent of of his death to you, and a <hi>fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> of the efficacy of his death in you, will raiſe up your hearts to a high meaſure of <hi>admiration, eſtimation,</hi> and <hi>affection</hi> of him, and to him. After you have knowne the death of Chriſt, and the benefits thereby <hi>(viz. the put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting avvay of your ſins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 9.25. Epheſ. 2.14. Firſt labour to be Gods ſons, and then his publique ſer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vauts, as <hi>Chriſt</hi> was.</note> 
               <hi>making peace betvveen God &amp; your perſons; &amp; making ſure your ſalvation)</hi> Then conſider, and ſtudy the goodnes of his nature, the goodlineſſe his perſon, the greatneſſe of his love, the freeneſſe and ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches of his grace, the ſweetneſſe and preciouſneſſe of his promiſes, the beauty and comelineſſe of his Church, and people, and the tranſcendency and eternity of his glory.</p>
            <p>The beſt, next, and ſureſt way to become ſound and true Chriſtians, is to know that Christ hath done all for you,<note place="margin">Iſa. 26.12. Phil. 2.12, 13.</note> and without you, and that he must doe all in you, and by you. And being true Chriſtians, (which is the wel-being of men) to live on him, and walke to him, who hath given you the name, and the nature, which makes you to be ſo ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted. And ſeeing God hath honoured, &amp; glorified his Sonne, after hee had finiſhed his worke, let that encourage you <hi>(Honourable Senatours)</hi> to goe on in the work that God hath called you too: Chriſt hath done, and ſuffered much for you, Oh be you willing to do, and to ſuffer for him alſo. Doubtleſſe if you own his <hi>cauſe</hi> &amp; <hi>croſſe</hi> &amp; chooſe his <hi>will,</hi> and doe his <hi>work,</hi> as he hath put <hi>chains</hi> of gold about your necks here, ſo he will put <hi>crowns</hi> of gold upon your heads hereafter.<note place="margin">Luk. 16.2, 3, 4.</note> Remember you are Stewards entru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted with your Maſters treaſure, and muſt give an account you know not how ſoone, be ſure therefore you lay out all for your Lords glory, and the good of his Family. Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevere in the way you have begun, and proſecute the good
<pb facs="tcp:117698:3"/>worke you have entred upon (eſpecially your late &amp; excellent Petition.) Stand far, (and ſtrive together) to obtaine the pure <hi>Goſpel,</hi> to guide mens ſouls in ſpirituall things, and plaine <hi>Laws</hi> to direct men in civill things. Be for Christ reſolutely, and for true Chriſtians really: execute juſtice impartially, regard, and relieve the oppreſſed and needy ſpeedily,<note place="margin">Neh. 6.3.</note> and ſay as <hi>Nehemiah</hi> ſaid, <hi>I am doing a great worke, why ſhould the worke ceaſe whilſt I leave it?</hi> Doe not take off your hand from the Lords plough this yeare, for this may be the year of <hi>viſitation,</hi> and the next of <hi>jubilee.</hi> The greateſt honour is like to be lost or got this yeare: the Lord be honoured by you, and honour you in himſelfe. Which is, and ſhall be the prayers of him that craves your pardon for his boldneſe, rudeneſſe of ſpeech, and for adding one <hi>uſe,</hi> which time prevented me then, to deliver.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Maſter Chriſts ſervant, in his, and at your ſervice, <hi>VAVASOR POWELL.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117698:3"/>
            <head>GOD the FATHER glorified: And the work of mens <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> finiſhed by JESVS CHRIST on Earth.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>John 17.4.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>I have glorified thee on the earth, I have finiſhed the work which then goveſt me to doe.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE laſt Lords day, Right Honourable and Beloved,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>By Mr.</hi> Thomas Goodwin.</note> you had preſented un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you the <hi>Dedication</hi> of Chriſt (or Chriſt dedicating himſelfe) to the work of mens <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> I have choſen this Text (and I hope by the guidance of Gods ſpirit, it comes in ſeaſonably) to make known the work it ſelfe, even that great work or buſineſſe which Chriſt did (and none elſe could doe) upon earth. Chriſt tells you in this Text what it was, and wherein is did conſiſt.</p>
            <p>Before I come to the Text it ſelfe, I muſt firſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint you, how that our bleſſed Lord and Maſter <hi>Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> being to take his leave of his Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, he expreſſes at his departure moſt of his affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction to them. As <hi>Joſeph</hi> before he took his leave of his brethren<note n="a" place="margin">Gen. 45.1.4.15.</note> , made known himſelf unto them, kiſt them, and wept upon them: So Jeſus Chriſt, hee as
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117698:4"/>it were gives kiſſes of love, and ſhews more expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions of endearedneſſe, and renderneſſe towards his Diſciples at the time of his departure from them then he had done before, though he alwayes loved them; and there were foure ſpeciall expreſſions of Chriſts affection then ſhewed to them.</p>
            <p>The firſt was his carriage, his humble carriage; yee know how he humbled himſelfe, to<note n="b" place="margin">John 13.12.</note> 
               <hi>waſh his Diſciples feet:</hi> an expreſſion, and greater expreſſion of humility we have not in the Scripture. And this adds unto it, if you conſider the perſon that did it, and the perſons for whom it was done. The perſon that did it, was<note n="c" place="margin">Pſalm 24.7.9, 10.</note> 
               <hi>the King of glory.</hi> The perſons for whom it was done, they were <hi>poore Fiſhermen;</hi> this is a good example, and is was done that it might be an example for great men, and high Chriſtians, to condiſcend to them of low degree.</p>
            <p>The ſecond expreſſion was his heavenly counſell. In the 13, 14, 15, and 16. Chapters, he gives them many ſweet<note n="d" place="margin">John 13.14.17.19 34. and Chap 14.1.11.27, 28 &amp; 15.89, 10, 12.17.20. &amp; 16.33.</note> exhortations, many ſpirtuall admo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitions, many heavenly counſels, and cordiall ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices and directions.</p>
            <p>The third expreſſion of his affection to them, was his ſoule-ſtaying<note n="e" place="margin">John 14.2, 3.13, 14 16, 17, 18, 20.21.23.26.28. &amp; 15.7 26 &amp; 16.7. 23, 24.26.</note> promiſes; mark how many, and what ſuitable promiſes he makes to them, he ſaith that <hi>he will goe to prepare a place for them, and that hee will come again unto them, and that whatſoever they ſhould aske in his name, hee would doe it: Alſo, that he would pray the Father for the ſpirit the Comforter, that he might abide with them.</hi> Further he promiſet <hi>that they ſhould know that they were in him, and he in them: and that hee would love them, and manifest himſelfe unto them,</hi> and fetch them to himſelfe, and take them up into his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:117698:4"/>glory. Theſe together, with many other promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, were very powerfull to ſtay the drooping ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits, and the ſinking hearts of his Diſciples.</p>
            <p>The fourth and laſt expreſſion of Chriſts affection to them was his prayer, and his prayer you have in this Chapter: where you are to conſider,
<list>
                  <item>1. To whom he prayed.</item>
                  <item>2. For whom he prayed.</item>
                  <item>3. When he prayed.</item>
                  <item>4. For what he prayed.</item>
                  <item>5. How he prayed.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>I ſhall only touch theſe things becauſe they are in the way to the Text.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to whom he prayed: He prayed to his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and to him only.</p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, For whom he prayed, he pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,<note n="f" place="margin">Chap. 17. v. 1.</note>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, for <hi>himſelfe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Secondly, for his <hi>Apoſtles.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Thirdly, for thoſe that <hi>ſhould believe in him.</hi> Firſt, for <hi>himſelfe</hi> in the 5. verſe of this Chapter; then for the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> in the 9. verſe; then for thoſe that ſhould belive, in the 20. verſe, that's the ſecond thing.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Then thirdly, <hi>when</hi> did he pray this prayer?<note place="margin">Its obſervable that Chriſt, though ſo near to his paſſive obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience and ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, yet did not neglect his act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ive obedience, &amp; that in themidſt of his care for himſelfe, he did not omit in ſlew his care of his Diſciples. <hi>Verſe 1.</hi>
               </note> it was a little before his agony came upon him, a little before <hi>Judas</hi> came to apprehend him, as you ſhall finde in the 3. firſt verſes of the next Chapter, <hi>when Jeſus had ſpoken theſe words, viz.</hi> his counſels, pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>miſes and prayers, <hi>hee went forth with him Diſciples ever the brooke Kedron,</hi> where was a garden; into which hee intred, &amp;c. whether <hi>Iudas</hi> with his baſe band of men came to apprehend him. Then</p>
            <p>Fourthly, you have the matter of his prayer here,
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117698:5"/>or what he prayed for: He prayes for himſelf, that he might be glorified. He prayes for his people that they might<note n="g" place="margin">Verſe 15.</note> be <hi>kept from the evil, i. e.</hi> the evill of ſinne eſpecially, that they might be <hi>ſanctified</hi> and<note n="h" place="margin">Verſe 21.23.</note> 
               <hi>made one,</hi> or <hi>made perfect in one,</hi> and that they might be<note n="i" place="margin">Verſe 24.</note> with him to behold his glory; theſe are the main things in his prayer.</p>
            <p>The fifth and laſt thing confiderable,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="5"/> is the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how he did pray.</p>
            <p>Firſt, he prayed very familiarly and confidently, he cals God his Father;<note n="k" place="margin">Verſe 1.5. 11:21:24, 25.</note> ſixe times in this one pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er he calls him Father: One while, <hi>Oh Father,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther while, <hi>rghteous Father,</hi> another while, <hi>holy Father,</hi> all words of affection and confidence, and expreſſing much of the ſpirit of Sonneſhip, a good<note n="l" place="margin">See Iſa. 63.16 &amp; 64.8. Mat. 6.9. Rom. 8.15. Gal. 4.6.</note> example for Saints.</p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, as he prayed confidently, ſo he prayed compendiouſly. Chriſts prayer was not a very long prayer; and I confeſſe this, that I think it to be contrary to the Goſpel to make very long prayers: The Scribes and Phariſees are<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <hi>Math. 23.14.</hi> Its true, that Chriſt did not ſo much reproves them for their prayer as their hypocriticall end &amp; prex nor in praying.</note> noted, if not reproved for it: And Chriſt when hee teaches the<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat. 6, 7, 8, 9. &amp;c.</hi>
               </note> Diſciples to pray, he gives them a ſhort forme; <hi>Solomon</hi> alſo<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eccl. 5.2.</hi> Thou canſt not be too frequent and ſpiritual in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, but thou maiſt be too lone, and pump in thy own dry, heart when the water of the ſpirit <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſaith, <hi>let thy words be few.</hi> I finde Jeſus Chriſts prayers, the Apoſtles prayers, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets prayers all to be ſhort. I ſay not but there is a difference between time, and time; occaſion and oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion: Againe, I ſay not this to give advantage to graceleſſe men that pray not at all, and condemn o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; neither doe I ſay it to take off men from pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or from being long in prayer when the Spirit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds in them. Sometimes people may pray long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er then ordinary, as particularly when people ſeeke God by faſting.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:117698:5"/>
The third thing in his prayer was this, that he did pray argumentatively, he uſed arguments<note n="p" place="margin">John 17. v. 1.4, 5, 10, 11.24.</note> anſwe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable to every petition that he prayed for: not that he needed to uſe ſuch arguments, but doubtleſſe to leave it upon record for all believers.</p>
            <p>Thus having made way to my Text, you are to conſider it as an argument that Jeſus Chriſt uſed when he prayed, that he might be glorified; and it may be joyned either to to the firſt or 5. verſ. <hi>I have glorified thee upon the earth, I have finiſhed the work which thou gavest me to doe, and now O father glorifie thou me;</hi> as if ſo be Chriſt ſhould have ſaid, Father, thou didſt ſend me into the world to glorifie thee, and to work <hi>Redemption,</hi>
               <note place="margin">I apprehend that Chriſt prais here for a double glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>viz.</hi> the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry due to him as a Sonne, which was his naturall and birth-right glory; and the glory due to him for his ſervice as Mediator, <hi>v. 1. &amp; 5.</hi> compared together.</note> and purchaſe <hi>Salvation</hi> for as many as thou gaveſt me; theſe things I have done, and now I am upon leaving the world again, and retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to thee, therefore glorifie me as thy <hi>Son,</hi> with that glory which I had with thee before the world was; alſo glorifie me as a Mediator. <hi>Righteous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> I deſire thee to conſider that I doe not aske a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny thing that is unreaſonable; for ſeeing I have glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified thee upon <hi>Earth,</hi> glorifie thou me in <hi>Heaven:</hi> Seeing alſo I have finiſhed the work thou gaueſt me to doe, glorifie me thy Son with thy ſelfe.</p>
            <p>The words contain in them three things.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> what Chriſts great buſineſſe and worke upon earth was, to wit, to glorifie God his Father, and to work the work of mens <hi>redemption</hi> &amp; <hi>ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2 Then ſecondly you have in the Text,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhment of this buſineſſe and worke of his, in theſe words, <hi>I have finiſhed the worke which thou gaveſt me to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then thirdly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> the motives that moved Jeſus
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:117698:6"/>Chriſt to do this worke,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> and theſe are two: 1. be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it was his Fathers worke; ſo much is included in the Text.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> 2. Becauſe his Father gave him this worke to do; this is expreſſed, <hi>the work which thou gaveſt me to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>There be but two things in the Text to be open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and explained, and then I come to the Doctrine.</p>
            <p>Q. The firſt is this, <hi>How doth it appeare, that this worke ſpoken of by Ieſus Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">The two diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culties in the Text explained.</note> 
               <hi>was the worke of mens</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, <hi>and the worke of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſalvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> By comparing it with other Scriptures, and we have ſeverall other Scriptures,<note place="margin">Hab. 1.5 with Acts 13.41.</note> that ſpeake of this worke of redemption and ſalvation, as <hi>Hab.</hi> 1.5. <hi>I will worke a worke in your dayes, which ye will not believe though it be told you.</hi> If you compare this with <hi>Acts</hi> 13.41. you wil find it to be the work of Redemption and Salvation; this is that worke, or the worke, the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the maine and chiefe worke that Chriſt was to do, and this worke he cals his Fathers work, in <hi>Iohn</hi> 4 34. <hi>My meat and drinke is to do the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But there are many works of Chriſt ſpoken of in the Goſpell, as his work of miracles, his worke of preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the like.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> It is true,<note place="margin">Math. 11.2 &amp; 13.54. John 5.20. &amp; 10.25.32.37, 38.</note> the working of miracles, and of preaching, were the workes of Chriſt, &amp; diſtinct works; but thoſe were comprehended (as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards I ſhall ſhew) in that of glorifying God, and carrying on mens Redemption.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q</hi> The ſecond thing here, is, <hi>How could Chriſt ſay he had finiſhed the worke, ſeeing he had not yet ſuffered? ſurely the worke of mens Redemption, &amp; the work of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was not finiſhed, till Chriſt had ſuffered; how then
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117698:6"/>ſaith Chriſt here, I have finiſhed the worke.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> 1. I ſhall cleer that by another Text, which is in the 2d of <hi>Timothy</hi> the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> and the 7<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, where <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>I have finiſhed my courſe;</hi> and yet you know <hi>Paul</hi> was not dead then, he did live peradventure ſome years after that; at leaſt he did live ſome what lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and did ſome ſervice afterwards, though he ſaith. <hi>He had finiſhed his couſe.</hi> 2 The word that is in the Creek (for it is but one) and tranſlated, <hi>I have niſhed,</hi> it ſignifies not only perfecting of a work, but it ſignifies a going on with a work, alſo it ſignifies to offer, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſecrate, &amp; ſacrifice; yea it ſignifies a going through with a work, though it be not finiſhe; The<note n="q" place="margin">John 17.4. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2 Tim. 4.7. <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> ſame word that Chriſt uſeth here, <hi>Paul</hi> uſed (though it is not in the ſame tenſe) &amp; doubtleſſe the meaning of it is this, that Jeſus Chriſt he had undertaken &amp; proceeded very far in the worke of mans redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in the work of ſalvation; he had alſo reſolved fully that he would not lay aſide that work, till hee had perfectly compleated it, and ſo you are to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it; as oft times men uſe to ſpeak when they purchaſe a thing that they have bought it, &amp; ended that bargain, though they have not paid for it.</p>
            <p>Now having openned the words, take notice of this ſpeciall and ſpirituall obſervation from them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To glorifie God, and to work the work of mens redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and ſalvation,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dact.</note> 
               <hi>was the buſineſſe of Ieſus Chriſt upon earth and this buſineſſe he hath finiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beloved, I know not any ſubject in all the word of God, that is ſo neceſſary to be ſpoken of as this ſubject is, the <hi>glory of God,</hi> the <hi>worke of Redemption,</hi> and the <hi>worke of Salvation;</hi> every man is concerned therein, and it behoves every man to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117698:7"/>know this truth, not only Magiſtrates, but alſo o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther people; yea, every man that hath a ſoule, hee ought to be acquainted with this truth and doctrine. To proceed herein,</p>
            <p>I ſhall firſt <hi>prove</hi> this Doctrine to you by the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Secondly, <hi>cleare</hi> it and explain it.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, give you ſome <hi>reaſons</hi> to confirme it, and teach you what <hi>uſes</hi> you are to make of it.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>proofe</hi> of this Doctrine, that the work of Jeſus Chriſt upon earth was to glorifie his Father, and work the work of mans redemption and ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and this he hath finiſhed.</p>
            <p>There are two things to be proved.</p>
            <p>Firſt, That to glorifie God was his work; for this take one Text in the 7. of <hi>Iohn,</hi> verſ. 18. <hi>Hee that ſpeaketh of himſelfe ſeeketh his own glory;</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 7.18.</note> but <hi>he that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth his glory that ſent him, the ſame is true, &amp; no unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous neſs is in him.</hi> Here Jeſus Chriſt tells you, that he did ſeeke the glory of him that ſent him, which was God the Father.</p>
            <p>Then to prove that hee hath wrought mans <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption;</hi> you have a Text in the firſt of <hi>Luke,</hi> verſe 69.70.<note place="margin">Luke 1.69.70.</note> 
               <hi>Bleſsed be the Lord God of Iſrael, for he hath vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſited and redeemed his people.</hi> Mark, he ſaith he <hi>hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed them,</hi> though they were not as yet actually redeemed, <hi>and hath raiſed up for us a horne of ſalvation out of the houſe of his ſervant</hi> David. He ſpeaks here of Jeſus Chriſt that was the ſtrength of ſalvation, or one that was to work it by power and might, and therefore called here the horn of ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Then to prove that Jeſus Chriſt came to ſave, or to worke mens ſalvation: that you have in the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117698:7"/>18. of <hi>Matthew,</hi> the 11.<note place="margin">Matt. 18.11.</note> I <hi>came</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to ſeek end to ſave that which was loſt;</hi> and,</p>
            <p>Secondly, That the worke is finiſhed, the text it ſelfe is ſufficient for it. You have alſo other texts where he ſaith that it is finiſhed. As in the 19. of <hi>Iohn</hi> he ſaith theſe words, <hi>It is finiſhed.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 19.30.</note> What is finiſhed? Why all the Prophecies concerning me are now finiſhed, the worke of mans redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is now finiſhed. When he was upon the Croſs. Chriſt aſſerts this truth, that all was finiſhed.</p>
            <p>Now having proved the Doctrine, I ſhall in the next place come to cleere it, and for the cleering of it, reſolve theſe three queſtions.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt, what it is to glorifie God.</item>
               <item>Secondly, How did Jeſus Chriſt glorifie God?</item>
               <item>Thirdly, How did Chriſt finiſh the work of mens redemption, and the work of mens ſalvation? theſe are the three things to be opened.</item>
            </list>
            <p>Q. Firſt, <hi>What it is to glorifie God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> You muſt conſider that the Scriptures,<note place="margin">What it is to glorifie God?</note> ſpeak of this under ſeverall words, and notions; as ſometimes, it is to<note n="r" place="margin">Exod. 15.2. Eſa. 25.1.</note> exalt the Lord, ſometimes it is to<note n="ſ" place="margin">Pſal. 34.3. Luke 1.46.</note> magnifie him, ſometimes it is to<note n="t" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.17. Heb. 2.7.</note> honour him, ſometimes it is to<note n="u" place="margin">Pſal. 30.1. Dan. 4.37.</note> extoll and advance him, and all theſe words they are ſynonima's, and of the ſame nature and ſignification, and hold forth the ſame truth to us.</p>
            <p>But to anſwer it more particularly, to glorifie God is this, <hi>it is to ſet forth God in all his excellencies,</hi> or to make knowne God in all that he is, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge him in all that he doth, this I ſay is to glorifie God, to <hi>ſet forth God in all his excellencies,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:117698:8"/>thus did the Lord Jeſus Chriſt doe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>one did ever ſet out God, like unto Jeſus Chriſt; God was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſeen in any man, as he was ſeen in Chriſt, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in any mans words or works; And therefore it is ſaid in the firſt of <hi>Iohn,</hi> the eighteenth verſe, <hi>That the onely begotten ſon,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 1.18.</note> 
               <hi>who is in the boſome of the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he hath declared him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 17.26.</note> And in this 17. Chapter and the twenty ſixth verſe, ſaith Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>I have declared unto them thy name, and I will declare it, that the Love wherewith thou haſt loved me, may be in them, and I in them. I have declared unto them thy name,</hi> If you ask me what is meant there by <hi>Name?</hi> I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer, <hi>Name,</hi> it is taken variouſly in Scripture, ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times for perſon.<note n="x" place="margin">Acts 4.12.</note> 
               <hi>There is no other name given un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der heaven whereby we muſt be ſaved, i. e.</hi> no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon. Beſides, Chriſts name is alſo ſometimes taken for for<note n="y" place="margin">Exod. 3.18. &amp; 20.7. &amp; 33.19. Pſal. 8.1.</note> Gods attri-butes, as his <hi>wiſdome, mercy, goodneſſe, power,</hi> and it is taken alſo for <hi>glory</hi> and <hi>excellency,</hi> and here perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture may be meant all theſe. I have declared unto them, Oh Lord, thy <hi>being,</hi> thy <hi>power,</hi> thy <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties,</hi> thy <hi>grace,</hi> thy <hi>goodneſſe,</hi> thy <hi>excellency</hi> and thy <hi>glory,</hi> I have declared all theſe unto my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in the world.<note place="margin">Pſal. 76.1.</note> And ſo we have the word <hi>Name</hi> in 76. <hi>I ſalme</hi> and the firſt verſe. <hi>In Iudah is God known his name is great in Iſrael,</hi> that is, his power is great, his glory is great, his renowne, and dignity is great in Iſrael; amongſt his owne people of any other, there the <hi>Lord</hi> is more ſpecially preſent, and more clearely known;<note place="margin">Exod. 23.21.</note> So the Lord in the 23. of <hi>Exodus,</hi> and the 21. ver. bids the Iſraelites <hi>fear the Angel that he ſent before them, beware of him</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117698:8"/>obey his voyce, provoke him not, for he will not pardon your tranſgreſsion,</hi> for my <hi>Name</hi> is in him. This An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gell was <hi>Chriſt,</hi> this <hi>name</hi> that was in him, was his fathers <hi>honour, power,</hi> and <hi>glory:</hi> well, thus you heare the firſt thing opened.</p>
            <p>Q. The ſecond thing to be opened is this, <hi>How did Ieſus Chriſt glorifie his father, or glorifie God:</hi> For he ſaith <hi>I have glorified thee upon earth?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>A.</hi> Three wayes Jeſus Chriſt glorified him upon earth, (for thats the thing I am to ſpeak of,<note place="margin">How Chriſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified God?</note> and not how he glorifies him in heaven,) I ſay three wayes, he glrorified him, <hi>negatively, poſitively,</hi> and <hi>paſsively.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt negatively, Jeſus Chriſt did glorifie his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, theſe two wayes, negatively.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In that he did not ſinne, for as ſin is<note n="z" place="margin">Rom. 2.23.</note> a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honour unto God, ſo non-ſinning is an honour un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God. Jeſus Chriſt did glorifie his father very much in this he did never ſinne againſt him; no,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt did not ſinne.</note> he did never commit the leaſt evill. The Apoſtle <hi>Peter</hi>
               <note n="a" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21.</note> ſaith, <hi>he did no ſinne, neither was there guile found in his mouth,</hi> not the leaſt fraud, not the leaſt vaine word, not the leaſt hypocriſie found in Jeſus Chriſt, and this did tend much to glorifie God his father.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Ieſus Chriſt did glorifie his father ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatively,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> thus, by denying himſelfe,<note place="margin">Chriſt did not ſeek himſelfe.</note> by not ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing himſelfe, and this is a ſpeciall way to glorifie God, and this ſpeciall way did Chriſt glorifie him,<note place="margin">John 8.50.</note> as you may finde in the eigth of <hi>Iohn,</hi> and the fifty verſe. <hi>I ſeek not my owne glory, there is one that ſeeketh and judgeth:</hi> hete he denies his owne glory. So you finde when the people would have made him a King, he<note n="b" place="margin">John 6.15.</note> would not be made a King, he knew that
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117698:9"/>his father was God and King, and did he deny himſelfe, and this did tend much to the glory of God. As a child when hee is bare-headed and ſilent before his father,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vide</hi> Heb. 5.5.</note> when hee reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renceth and reſpects his Father, and does nothing but what he commands, and ſeeks nothing but what he gives him, you know the child thereby honours his Father, thus did the Lord Ieſus Chriſt doe, and thats the firſt way negatively.</p>
            <p>The ſecond way he glorified God,<note place="margin">Second way.</note> was <hi>poſitive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> and this he did alſo two wayes. By his words, and by his works.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt by his words, namely by his preaching,<note place="margin">Chriſt glorified his Father, by his words by his <hi>preaching.</hi>
               </note> by his praying, and by his confeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion; he did glorifie God mightily, by his preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, when the people heard him <hi>they wondered at the gracious words that proceeded out of his mouth, and</hi> its ſaid he (or God in him)<note n="c" place="margin">Luke 4.15. <hi>By his</hi> Prayer.</note> 
               <hi>was glorified of all.</hi> Then by his prayer he glorified God.<note n="d" place="margin">John 12.28.</note> 
               <hi>Glorifiethy name</hi> in one place,<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 26.39. <hi>By his</hi> confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> 
               <hi>and not my will but thine,</hi> in another place; thus his prayer tended to glorifie God. His confeſſion alſo did glorifie him,<note n="f" place="margin">John 10.29. <hi>and</hi> 14.28.</note> 
               <hi>My Father</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>is greater then I,</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">John 5.19.30.</note> againe, <hi>I can doe nothing of my ſelfe, but the works that my Father doth, thoſe doe I;</hi> thus by his words he glorified him.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Then by his <hi>works</hi> he did glorifie God very much, and I pray note this, that when Chriſt wrought miracles by the power of his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, the people did wonder, and give glory to God. You have this eight times at leaſt in the New Teſtament, I ſhall onely give you two texts<note n="h" place="margin">Matt. 9.8. &amp; 15.31. Mark 2.12. Luke 7.16. &amp; 13.13. &amp; 17.15. &amp; 23.47.</note> , the firſt is in the ninth of <hi>Matthew</hi> the eigth verſe, <hi>when the multitude ſaw it, they marvelled, and glorified God.</hi> So when they ſaw how Chriſt cured the man ſick of the Palſie, its ſaid they glorified God. Theſe
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:117698:9"/>great and mighty works that Ieſus Chriſt did upon earth, they had a tendency in them to exalt, and glorifie the Lord, and this is the ſecond way Ieſus Chriſt glorified his Father.</p>
            <p>The third way was <hi>paſsively,</hi> that is,<note place="margin">Third way.</note> by his <hi>ſufferings,</hi> Chriſt glorified his Father, I ſay he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſied him by his <hi>ſufferings,</hi> as much as any way elſe,<note place="margin">Chriſt glorified his Father by his ſufferings. <hi>John 13.31.</hi>
               </note> and therefore ſaith Chriſt in the 13. of <hi>Iohn,</hi> the 31th. verſe, <hi>Now is the Son of man glorified, and God is glorified in him,</hi> when was that <hi>now?</hi> then when Chriſt was going to ſuffer, in the ſufferings of Jeſus Chriſt, his Father was very much glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> I, But you will ſay, Sir, how was the Father glorified in Chriſts ſufferings, one would thinke that the Father ſhould be rather diſhonoured then glorified thereby, in ſuffering his Sonne to fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the hands of ſuch cruell enemies, as the Jewes and Heathens were to God, we cannot ſee how this did tend to the glory of God?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I anſwer,<note place="margin">By his patient ſufferings.</note> it tended to the glory of God thus, 1. By Chriſts patience under his ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferings, to ſee Chriſt ſo patient, under ſuch a great meaſure, and ſo heavie a weight of affliction, this glorifyed God very much; he did not ſo much as<note n="i" place="margin">Eſa. 53.7.</note> open his mouth, to complaine of his condition, nor of his enemies cruelty; as the young men in<note n="k" place="margin">Dan. 3.</note> 
               <hi>Daniel,</hi> when they were caſt into the fiery Furnace, they acknowledged the onely true God, and they would own no other, alſo they would not be freed, if they might not be freed without ſin: ſo Jeſus Chriſt would goe through the worke of his father, and glorifye him, as the expreſſion is, even,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:117698:10"/>
               <hi>in the fires,</hi> even in the fire of affliction, yea, in the Furnace of affliction.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Chriſt glorifyed his father in this, when he was delivering up the Ghoſt, <hi>The vaile of the Temple was rent in twaine,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 27.51.</note> 
               <hi>and the earth did quake:</hi> Yea, the heathens ſaid, when they ſaw this, <hi>that ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the God of nature was now dying, or elſe that the end of the world was come upon them.</hi> This tended much to the glorifying of God; the Jewes and Gentiles that would never glorifie him before theſe ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of Chriſt, and this act of his death; yet doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs, this, did work upon them. As you know when a <hi>Comedy</hi> is played, people are not ſo ſeriouſly and deepely affected, as when a <hi>Tragedy</hi> is acted: ſo when Jeſus Chriſt was upon the earth; they were not ſo much affected with him, neither did they ſo much glorifie God in him: but when he was acting this <hi>Trygiccall part,</hi> or his <hi>ſufferings,</hi> doubtleſſe then many of the Jewes were convinced; and thats the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of that text,<note place="margin">John 12.32.</note> in the 12. of <hi>Iohn</hi> the 32. <hi>When the Son of man is lifted up, he ſhall draw all men (or many) unto him, this ſpeaks he of his death;</hi> when Chriſt was exalted upon the Croſſe, many were perſwaded that this was the Son of God. <hi>Truly,</hi> ſay they, <hi>this was the Sonne of God.</hi> And againe, Chriſt ſaith in the 12th. of <hi>Iohn,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 12.24.</note> ver. 24. <hi>Except a corne of wheat fall into the ground and dye, it cannot bring forth.</hi> Shewing, that except Jeſus Chriſt, that was that corne of wheat, ſhould die and ſuffer, there ſhould little profit come unto men, and little glory unto God. And thus is the next queſtion anſwered, how Jeſus Chriſt glorifyed his father, Firſt negatively by not ſinning, and not ſeeking himſelfe.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:117698:10"/>
Secondly, <hi>poſitively</hi> by his word, and works.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, <hi>paſsively</hi> by his ſufferings.</p>
            <p>The next and the laſt queſtion for the cleering of the text is this:</p>
            <p>Q. <hi>How did Jeſus Chriſt finiſh the work of mens re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption, the work of mens ſalvation?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I beſeech you ſtirre up your ſelves, and hearken unto this, Jeſus Chriſt did finiſh the work of mens redemption, and the work of mens ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion three wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The firſt way was this,<note place="margin">The firſt way Chriſt wrought mens Redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and falvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</note> by putting himſelf into mans condition, that's the firſt; Jeſus Chriſt he did put himſelfe into the ſtate, and condition of men, he comes from Heaven, and takes up mans nature, he appeares in mans fleſh, and undergoes the ſtate and condition of men, (yea ſinfull men) and if you conſider but what the Scripture ſpeaks of this, it will be a great encouragement for you to looke for ſalvation through Jeſus Chriſt. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider Chriſt therefore two wayes, Firſt as a <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atour,</hi> and ſecondly, as a <hi>Surety.</hi> As a <hi>Mediatour,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt conſider-as a Mediator.</note> He is ſaid to be Mediatour of the New Teſtament, <hi>There is one Mediator between God man, the man Chriſt Ieſus,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.4.<note place="margin">1 Tim. 2.4.</note> There was but one mediator be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween God, and men, from eternity. Its true <hi>Moſes</hi> was a typicall mediator; but there was no reall and true <hi>Mediator</hi> ſave Jeſus Chriſt only; And as the Apoſtle ſaith in the third of the <hi>Galathians</hi> the 20. v. <hi>Now a Mediator</hi> (marke this) <hi>Is not a Mediator of one,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 3.20.</note> 
               <hi>but God is one,</hi> what is the meaning of that? The meaning is, that Chriſt was not a Mediator of <hi>one Covenant,</hi> that is of the <hi>Covenant of works</hi> onely, but a Mediator of the Covenant of grace alſo: Or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117698:11"/>thus, Chriſt was a <hi>Mediator</hi> betweene one and not as a <hi>dayes man,</hi> or Mediator among men, for we never uſe a <hi>Mediator</hi> to reconcile a man to himſelfe, but a dayes-man goes to reconcile two that are at vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance: But Jeſus Chriſt was a <hi>Medator</hi> of one, that is, he that was offended; and he that was <hi>Mediator</hi> to <hi>mediate</hi> for the offence, and to reconcile man unto himſelfe in one perſon. Was one and the ſame God the ſame God? That I may cleare this a little unto you, conſider what the word Mediator ſignifies.</p>
            <p>The greek word for a<note n="m" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Mediator,</hi> ſignifies as much as this, <hi>one that puts himſelfe as it were betweene an offending and offended party</hi> (yet not without a <hi>Call</hi> to reconcile them, and being an indifferent perſon and diſpoſed to either party: thus was Jeſus Chriſt, Only Chriſt had ſomewhat more to make him a Mediator, then Mediators among men have; to wit, he was not onely called to be a Mediator, but he was made a Mediator by<note n="n" place="margin">Heb. 7.20.</note> 
               <hi>Oath,</hi> to declare that he was to doe right between <hi>God</hi> and men, to give God his due and not to undoe poore man. So thus you heare that Jeſus Chriſt became a Media<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor, <hi>a midler,</hi> or <hi>middle perſon,</hi> between God and man.</p>
            <p>Now in the next place I ſhall ſhew you how Chriſt is a <hi>ſurety.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Chriſt conſidered as a ſurety. <hi>Heb. 7.22.</hi>
               </note> He is made ſaith the Apoſtle (in the 7th. of the <hi>Hebr.</hi> the 22. verſe) <hi>A Surety of a better teſtament,</hi> A Surety <hi>quaſi</hi> Sure-tye, not an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certaine tye, but a ſure-tye, a tye that can never be broken. Indeed the tye that was between God, and man in his <hi>Innocency,</hi> was a tye that was to be broken and untyed, but this is a ſure-tye, when God deals with men in Chriſt, he deales vvith them
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:117698:11"/>in a ſure way; and the word <hi>ſurety</hi> in the<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, as <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pirquo.</note> Greek comes of a verb that ſignifies to draw neer, for a ſurety is very neer to a debtor, becauſe he is joyned to him in the ſame <hi>bond</hi> and <hi>obligation;</hi> ſo commonly he that is ſurety for another, is neere to him either in <hi>relation,</hi> or <hi>habitation.</hi> Jeſus Chriſt he was neer, he came neer unto man, he came neer alſo unto mans nature, for he<note n="(p)" place="margin">Heb. 2.16.</note> took mans nature upon him; hee came neer to mans ſin, for he<note n="(q)" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.24</note> bore mans ſin upon him; this <hi>ſurety</hi> was very neer indeed; yea, you ſhall finde that hee was ſo neer, that by two expreſſions in the Scripture, you would thinke Jeſus Chriſt to be the very ſinner: <hi>Marke,</hi> the one is in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.21.<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.21.</note> 
               <hi>He was made</hi> (ſaith the Apoſtle) <hi>ſinne for us.</hi> He ſaith not, that he was counted a ſinner for us, but he was made ſinne in the very abſtract. It is more then if he had ſaid, he was accounted or made a ſinner for us; for he had indeed more then the ſinnes of <hi>one</hi> or <hi>thouſands,</hi> yea or <hi>millions</hi> upon him. Another expreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion you have in the third of the <hi>Galathians, verſe</hi> 13. where the Apoſtle ſaith, that <hi>Chriſt was made a curſe for us,</hi> for it is written,<note place="margin">Gal. 3.13.</note> 
               <hi>Curſed is every one that hangeth on a tree.</hi> He ſaith not, Chriſt was made ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed for us, but <hi>a curſe for us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh here was love, that Chriſt came from the boſome of the Father, and tooke upon him mans feeble nature; yea, he tooke upon him alſo the bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den of mans ſin, the debt that man owed to God, &amp; came in mans ſtead, to ſatisfie it, and was content that his Father ſhould deale with him as if hee had been the <hi>ſinner;</hi> yea he puts the <hi>ſinner</hi> out of the room, and he comes into the room himſelf, he blots out and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117698:12"/>cancels the name of the poore debtor, that was bound in this bond of the Law to God, and he puts himſelf in the bond, in the ſtead of him: only here was the difference between Chriſt and another ſure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; another <hi>ſurety,</hi> (or a ſurety amongſt men) comes in by the by, and is not content to be the <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall;</hi> but here Jeſus Chriſt becomes (though not by deſert, yet by <hi>principall</hi>) and takes upon himſelf the debt; he doth not ſay, <hi>Debtor</hi> do thou thy beſt, and I will do the reſt, no, he ſaith rather thus, <hi>poore diſtreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed debtor,</hi> I come to take thy debt upon me, and to ingage my ſelfe in thy ſtead to my Father, I'le take the Law, and the Curſe, and thy ſinne upon me, and I'le ſee whether I can goe through the buſineſſe, which thou canſt not; thus doth the Lord Ieſus Chriſt do; that is the firſt thing he puts himſelf into mans ſtead and condition.</p>
            <p>The ſecond thing that Ieſus Chriſt did,<note place="margin">Chriſt conquered the obſtructers and enemies of mens <hi>Redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion</hi> and <hi>Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
               </note> was to conquer and remove all mans enemies, that hindered mans <hi>redemption</hi> and <hi>ſalvation.</hi> I ſhall name ſome ſix enemies that did hinder mens <hi>redemption</hi> and <hi>ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and ſhew you how Ieſus Chriſt did conquer and remove them all.</p>
            <p>The firſt enemy (I beſeech you note it) was mans owne ſinne; ſinne is the<note n="(a)" place="margin">Rom. 5.12</note> cauſe of death, and man ſhould never have dyed, had not man ſinned; now ſinne did interpoſe, and intervene be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene God and man, and ſo did ſhut the doore of Gods mercy and grace, that man ſhould not come in. But Ieſus Chriſt hee comes and takes hold upon this enemy of mankinde, <hi>ſinne,</hi> and ſaith, <hi>ſinne,</hi> well thou and I muſt have a ſingle bout con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning theſe mens <hi>redemption</hi> and <hi>ſalvation;</hi> thou wouldeſt hinder men from being ſaved, I would
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117698:12"/>have them ſaved; thou wouldeſt ſhut the doore of my Fathers grace and glory from theſe men, and I would have it open; now I will try whether thou be ſtronger to keep them from glory, or I to bring them to glory; upon this, ſinne comes with all its number, cals in all its forces, yea all the ſinnes that have been committed, or ſhall be committed, from <hi>Adams</hi> time to the day of the <hi>reſurrection;</hi> all theſe ſinnes, I meane the <hi>ſinnes of thoſe that ſhall be ſaved,</hi> they came in together, and in heaps upon the Lord Jeſus Chriſt: Nay more (my beloved) God the Father, when he ſaw that his Sonne would needs undertake for mankinde, to ſave mankinde, he gathers all the ſinnes that were committed, or to be committed by any forementioned againſt him, and layes them upon the ſhoulders of his Sonne and did (as I may ſpeake with reverence) ſay thus to his <hi>Sonne, Well my Son,</hi> ſeeing thou haſt ſo much delight in the ſonnes and daughters of men, ſeeing thou wilt have them ſaved, and not damned, ſeeing thou wilt undergo what is due to their ſins ſince thou wilt be ſurety for them, I muſt reckon with thee, if thou wilt undergo the ſorrow, ſhame, and miſery that is due to their ſins, (I had rather take thy word, and have thee to ſatisfie me) yet looke thou to it, for all the ſins of thoſe that thou art willing to ſave thou muſt beare them, and ſatisfie for them, for I in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend not to reckon any more with ſuch ſinners, but I will put all upon thy <hi>ſcore</hi> and <hi>account.</hi>
               <note place="margin">The great wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingneſſe of Chriſt to ſuffer for mens ſinnes, <hi>Pſal. 40 7. Heb. 10.9.</hi>
               </note> Now Jeſus Chriſt might anſwer his Father thus, O Father, ſuch is my love, ſuch is my delight, and ſuch is my pitty towards the Sonnes of men, that I had rather undergo ten thouſand times ſo many ſinnes, yea ten
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117698:13"/>thouſand thouſand times ſo many ſufferings for ſin, then that theſe poor ſoules ſhould be damned: Now therefore Father bring all thy bils in, and let me ſee what theſe poor ſouls owe thee; for I am reſolved I will ſatisfie for them all, or let me die eternally, and periſh for ever. Upon this God the Father brings all mens ſinnes (<hi>i.e.</hi> all mens ſins that believe) and lays them upon Ieſus Chriſt, and Chriſt having ſatisfied for them, he removes them out of the way, and this is called a<note n="(a)" place="margin">Dan. 9.24.</note> 
               <hi>finiſhing of tranſgreſsion,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 1.29</note> 
               <hi>and making an end of ſin;</hi> and in another place, <hi>a taking away, or put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting away of ſin,</hi> Heb. 2.26. (farre enough out of mens ſight and reach) and this was typed out by<note n="(c)" place="margin">Levit. 16 8, 9, 10.26.</note> the Scapegoat under the Law. Obſerve this, that all the ſinne that God did intend to pardon, or ever will pardon, they were once laid<note n="d" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eſi. 53 6.</hi> Ged made them to meet upon him.</note> upon Chriſt, &amp; are now done away perfectly, and never to be imputed either to him or any of his.<note n="e" place="margin">Pſa. 85.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond enemy was Gods juſtice;<note place="margin">Gods juſtice till it was ſattsfyed. was a bar in the way of men, ſal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vation.</note> juſtice in God muſt be ſatisfied, or elſe there was no ſalvation to be expected or obtained; now Ieſus Chriſt (ſince he had undertook it) muſt a full ſatisfaction unto his Fathers juſtice, before he himſelf or any ſinner could be diſcharged or ſaved; but as ſoon as Chriſt had gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven ſatisfaction unto his Father, you ſhall ſee <hi>how ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and mercy,</hi> or <hi>righteouſneſſe and peace kiſſed together.</hi> That theſe like the<note n="(f)" place="margin">Exo. 25.20.</note> two <hi>Cherubims</hi> (<hi>with their wings and facts</hi>) did looke one towards another.<note place="margin">Exod. 28.29.</note> You have another excellent type of this, in that booke of <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus,</hi> the 28. <hi>chap.</hi> and the 29. <hi>verſe, And Aaron ſhall beare the names of the children of Iſrael, in the breſt plate of judgement, and thou ſhalt put on the breſt-plate, the judgement of Urim and Thummim, &amp;c.</hi> This <hi>Urim</hi> and
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117698:13"/>
               <hi>Thummim,</hi> the one did ſignifie, (it is probable,) the Prophetical Office Chriſts, &amp; the other the Prieſtly Office of Chriſt; <hi>Urim</hi> and <hi>Thummim</hi> ſignifies in the Hebrew, Lights and Perfection. There was aboun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of <hi>light</hi> in Chriſt, as a <hi>Prophet;</hi> abundance of <hi>perfection</hi> in Chriſt, as a <hi>Prieſt.</hi> Ann this I would have you note, <hi>as the Prieſt bore the judgement of the children of Iſrael,</hi> ſo Chriſt bore the judgment of his people. Now when juſtice was alſo ſatisfied, and even God the Father, to ſpeak with reverence, had no more juſtice left in himſelf againſt ſuch men, but what he brought out againſt Chriſt; &amp; when he had brought all his juſtice out, as you know when a man ſtands at the bar, either to be <hi>judged</hi> or <hi>juſtified,</hi> they will bring in all the matters, bills, and evidences, that may be found, or can be brought againſt ſuch a man: And when you ſee ſuch a one cleared, after all the <hi>Indictments</hi> that were brought in againſt him, ſurely you will ſay nothing can be laid to ſuch a mans charge; thus (as we may ſay) the Lords <hi>Statutes</hi> and <hi>Bills</hi> were brought in againſt the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, yet he did give perfect ſatisfaction to the juſtice of God, before ever he could be freed from that which was laid to his charge.</p>
            <p>A third enemy (that ſtood up againſt mens <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> and <hi>ſalvation</hi> which Jeſus Chriſt hath con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quered,<note place="margin">The law-hinde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red mens <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> and <hi>ſalvation.</hi>
               </note> and taken out of the way) was the <hi>Law</hi> (note that theſe two are diſtinct things) for the Law of God and juſtice, they differ as much, as juſtice in a Judge, and the Law by which he judgeth. <hi>Juſtice</hi> in a Judge, is not the Law, though he is to execute ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice according to the Law; now the Law of God came in againſt Chriſt, when Chriſt was to ſuffer, and the Law ſaid well, I muſt have obedience, ſayes
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:117698:14"/>the Law; Thou ſhalt, ſaith Chriſt; I muſt have perfect obedience ſayes the Law; Thou ſhalt, ſaith Chriſt; I muſt have perpetuall obedience, ſaith the Law; Thou ſhalt, ſaith Chriſt; I muſt have ſuch obedience, that I muſt be fully ſatisfied, that there be nothing in me, but muſt be fulfilled; Thou ſhalt ſaith Chriſt. Now, when Jeſus Chriſt had given to the Law its demands, and had fulfilled the Law by his <hi>active</hi> and <hi>pasſive</hi> obedience, and yeelded obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence inſtead of man, and paid for mans diſobedience too, he takes hold upon the <hi>Law,</hi> and ſaith to the <hi>Law,</hi> Now <hi>Law</hi> be ſure thou never comeſt againſt any of mine hereafter; come not and charge thoſe that are mine with the debt I have already paid; Law, have thou nothing to do to apprehend any of them that are my members, they are free men; now Law, ſee that thou intrude not into the conſciences of any of my people; for as thou didſt exact from me, ſo I require of thee that thou trouble not any of mine. Thus Chriſt having fulfilled the Law, becoms the <hi>end of the Law, for righteouſneſſe to every one that believeth.</hi> By the end of the Law; I meane the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect end of it, or the end of it as it was a Covenant of works;<note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Rom. 10.4</hi> Finis perficiens non interficiens.</note> requiring obedience upon pain of death &amp; damnation. Thus when Chriſt had perfectly ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed &amp; fulfilled th Law, the Law was laid up in Chriſt, as <hi>the Tables and Teſtimony were put in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Arke,</hi> which ſignified Chriſt, the Law being fulfilled and accompliſhed by Chriſt,<note n="(b)" place="margin">Exod. 25.16. Heb. 9.4.</note> it was to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinue no longer in force againſt ſuch as ſhould believe in him, &amp; now menare to receive the Law as handed out to them by Jeſus Chriſt,<note n="(c)" place="margin">1 Cor. 9.21.</note> and not to looke upon
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117698:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>it as a Covenant of works, and as it was handed and delivered by God to <hi>Moſes,</hi> and by <hi>Moſes</hi> to the children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> Well, this is the next thing, the Law is taken out of the way.</p>
            <p>The fourth enemy that ſtood up to pleade againſt a poore ſinner, and his <hi>redemption</hi> &amp; <hi>ſalvation</hi> was Satan; Satan ſtands up <hi>as the Philiſtim did;</hi> and ſaid, who is the man, that will redeeme theſe ſoules that are in my ſnare, and in my power? am not I God of all the earth? who ſhall deliver them out of my hands? Theſe great, high, and big words, like the words of the King of <hi>Aſſyria,</hi> were enough to terrifie and diſmay weake men. But the Lyon of the Tribe of <hi>Judah,</hi> he comes (as <hi>David</hi> againſt the <hi>Philiſtin</hi> and ſayes to him, ThouSatan, that haſt defied the Armies of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and haſtcaſt the Gantlet to all, and dareſt any man to fight with thee, and reſcue ſinfull men out of thy hands, try thy power, and pull downe thy pride, and I will, ſays Chriſt; hereupon Jeſus Chriſt comes and hath a ſingle duell with him, and the iſſue thereof was, that Satan wounded the heele of Chriſt, and Chriſt wounded his head, according to that ſaying,<note place="margin">(Gen.) 315.</note> 
               <hi>He ſhall bruiſe thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heele.</hi> That is, Satan ſhould have power againſt Chriſts body, to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come it, and Chriſt ſhould deſtroy his power. Therefore ſaith Chriſt, <hi>John</hi> 12.31.<note place="margin">Joh. 12.31.</note> 
               <hi>the Prince of this world be caſt out.</hi> So that now Satans power is already taken away; the Devill may challenge a right to many of Chriſts ſervants, till they are called, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted and brought from under his power; but alas! it is but an uſurped right, as a man that layes claime to a childes inheritance, when he is in his nonage, when the childe is not able, as yet, to maintaine his
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117698:15"/>right; ſo Satan layes claime to the ſoule, of a poore ſinner, as long as he is in his nonoge, till he comes to believe, but when a ſoule comes to the yeares of <hi>underſtanding regeneration,</hi> and <hi>adop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> then will he know that Satan hath nothing to doe to hinder his ſalvation, and this is the fourth enemy to mens <hi>redemption,</hi> and <hi>ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The fifth enemy that ſtood up againſt mens <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption</hi> and <hi>Salvation</hi> was the world; All the powers of the world they gathered together to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this worke; Firſt the Jewes (though they did not ahink it) gathered themſelves together, to hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der this worke of mens redemption; <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Alſo the heathens conſulted and concurred herein, yet all could not doe,<note place="margin">Acts 4.26.27.</note> but Chriſt tells and aſſures his Diſciples in the 16. of <hi>Iohn</hi> verſe 33. <hi>That he had overcome the world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">John 16.33.</note> ſo that all the <hi>ſnares</hi> in the world, all the <hi>temptations,</hi> all the pleaſures, all the <hi>deluſions,</hi> all the things in the world, and all the <hi>meu</hi> in the world could not hinder mens <hi>redemption</hi> and <hi>ſalvation,</hi> but Jeſus Chriſt overcome them all; <hi>be therefore of good cheare,</hi> for here is ground of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to ſinners, and Saints.</p>
            <p>Then the ſixt and laſt enemy that Jeſus Chriſt hath overcome, was death and hell,<note place="margin">Job. 18.14.</note> death you know is called the <hi>King of terrors,</hi> and there had need ſome great King come to overcome this King; therefore Jeſus Chriſt comes and undertakes and effects this worke, therefore <hi>Paul</hi> could ſay, (when he ſpeaks of the reſurrection of Christ, <hi>Oh death where is thy ſting, oh hell</hi> (or grave) <hi>where is thy victory?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.15.</note> death, come out, and let me ſee what thou canſt ſay againſt me, or believers? hath not my Lord Chriſt conquer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117698:15"/>and taken a way both the power and ſting,<note place="margin">Satan hath the power of death, and in is the ſting of death, but Chriſt hath overcome qoth. <hi>Heb. 2.14. 1 Cor. 15.56.</hi>
               </note> death and hell? they may fear believers with their ghaſtly looks, but death is but a bed to belieuers, it is but as a darke door out of the roome of grace into the roome of glory, out of the ſpiritual preſence of Chriſt into the glorious preſence of Chriſt. Thus I have opened the ſecond way how Jeſus Chriſt fini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the work of mens <hi>redemption</hi> &amp; <hi>ſalvation;</hi> one way was by putting himſelfe into their room &amp; place; And then ſecondly by removing, and conquering was in the way to hinder mens redemption, and mens ſalvation.</p>
            <p>And then thirdly, and laſtly,<note place="margin">Thirdly,</note> by purchaſing both the perſons and portions of men, or the men, and their glory.<note place="margin">Believers and their inheritance were purchaſed with an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable and preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous price.</note> Now Chriſt did not onely (remember this) remove ſinne, make ſatisfaction unto Juſtice, fulfill the Law, overcome Satan, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verthrow the world, and conquer death and hell, but hee did alſo purchaſe mens perſons, and mens porcions:</p>
            <p>Firſt he did purchaſe mens perſons, as the Apoſtle ſaith in the firſt of the <hi>Cor.</hi> the 6. and the laſt, <hi>Ye are bought with a price,<note n="l" place="margin">1 Cor. 6.20.</note> or with an honourable price,</hi> (as the word ſignifies; to wit,<note n="m" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.19.</note> 
               <hi>with the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious bloud of Chriſt.</hi> The Lord Jeſus hath bought the very haires of your heads, you that are believ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, or will believe, I ſay unto you, there is not a haire of your head falls to the ground, but Chriſt hath bought it, Marke that expreſſion of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>who loved (meaning Chriſt) the Church, and</hi>
               <note n="(n)" place="margin">Eph. 5.</note> 
               <hi>gave himſelfe for it;</hi> this doubtleſſe, was typed out in<note n="(o)" place="margin">Gen. 29.20.27, 28.</note> 
               <hi>Iacob,</hi> who bought his wife <hi>Rachell</hi> with 14. yeares hard ſervice. And<note n="(p)" place="margin">2 Sam. 3 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4.</note> 
               <hi>David,</hi> who bought
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117698:16"/>his wife with a <hi>hundred of foureskins of the Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſtines.</hi> Theſe three doubtleſs were types (as alſo others that bought their wives under the Law) of Jeſus Chriſt in this particular.</p>
            <p>Then ſecondly, he hath bought alſo the <hi>inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance</hi> and <hi>portion,</hi> which the Saints are to have for ever, in the firſt of the <hi>Epheſ.</hi> the 14. ver. the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle<note n="(q)" place="margin">Eph. 1.14.</note> ſaith that the ſpirit <hi>ſealed them unto the day of redemption, vntill the purchaſed poſſeſsion,</hi> that is, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till they come to obtaine what Chriſt hath pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſed for them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heaven is a gift and a purchaſe.</note> But is not Heaven a gift, how then doe you ſay it is purchaſed?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> The truth is, Heaven is a gift, but <hi>yet gift through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord.</hi> Rom. 6.23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj</hi> But if Chriſt purchaſed Heaven before, why doth he ſay, he goes to prepare a place for them? nay, what need he intercede for them?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> This is as a man that goes into a Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths ſhop, and buyeth Jewels there for his wife, and goes home to his wife, and ſaith, <hi>wife,</hi> I have bought ſuch and ſuch Jewels for thee, wilt thou goe and call for them, I ſaith ſhe, if you will goe along with me; he goes with her, and ſaith, deliver theſe Jewells to my wife; he purchaſeth them, not the laſt time, for he bought them before; So this is the difference betweene Chriſts <hi>death</hi> and <hi>interceſsion,</hi> by his <hi>death</hi> he purchaſed <hi>Heaven,</hi> and by his <hi>interceſsion,</hi> he deſires they may partake of <hi>Heaven;</hi> Chriſt did not goe to Heaven to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent there with his Father for it, but he went thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as a Bridegroome uſeth to doe, to make all ready againſt he brings his ſpouſe home. And
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117698:16"/>mark, when Chriſt <hi>intercedes</hi> in Heaveen, he doth it by his will; for as he once ſaid on earth, ſo he ſtill ſayes in Heaven<note n="(r)" place="margin">John 17.24</note> 
               <hi>I will that they may be where I am, that they may behold my glory.</hi> Now having opened the Doctrine, I'le give you but 2. reaſons (beſide <hi>Chriſt's teſtimony here</hi>) to prove that hee hath glorified his <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> and wrought the worke of mens <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt reaſon is this,<note place="margin">Reaſon 1.</note> becauſe elſe Chriſt ſhould never have entred into glory; note that, The Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle puts much up in this<note n="(s)" place="margin">1 Pet. 1.21.</note> 
               <hi>that God raiſed him up from the Dead and gave him glory.</hi> When Jeſus Chriſt had once come downe from heauen, and had undertaken this work, doubtleſſe there was no read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſions into heauen, till he had finiſhed it. If you ſhould ſee a Judge take a malefactor that had been arraigned before him at the barre, and lead him by the hand, and exalt him to ſit upon his own right hand, would you not conclude and ſay, ſurely this man is not onely acquitted from all that was laid to his charge, but hee is in great favour alſo with the Judge. Now God the Father, he judged &amp; condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned his Sonne; for if (I may ſo ſay) man had not ſo great a hand in the crucifying of Chriſt, as God had, <hi>mark,</hi> it is ſaid<note n="(t)" place="margin">Acts 4.28.</note> 
               <hi>that he was put to death by the determi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate counſel of God</hi> Now after his death God leads him out of his grave, into his glory, &amp; this was a ſign that there was nothing could be further laid to the charge of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> nor to the charge of ſuch that <hi>Chriſt</hi> did then undertake for. This is the argument of the Apoſtle, <hi>who ſhall lay any thing</hi>
               <note n="(u)" place="margin">Rom. 8.34</note> (ſaith he) <hi>to the charge of Gods electe it is Christ that dyed yea rather who is riſen, who alſo ſitteth at the right hand of God:</hi> and he puts a <hi>RATHER</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:117698:17"/>upon it; <hi>YEA RATHER, who is riſen, and fits upon the right hand of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſecond reaſon is this;<note place="margin">Reaſon 2.</note> becauſe that the Goſpel is now publiſhed unto men; wee ſhould never have had the Goſpel, had not Jeſus Chriſt finiſhed the work. You know till Chriſt was taken up into glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, there were <hi>two</hi> great things that were kept backe in heaven from men. Firſt, there was the ſpirit of God, And ſecondly, the counſell of God. Both theſe are wrap'd up in the Goſpel: Theſe two (I ſay) were kept backe from men till Chriſt had aſcended into heaven; but as ſoone as Jeaus Chriſt went up, the ſpirit immediately comes downe, and the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Lord begins to be revealed in a marvel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous way unto men: This is an abſolute and cleare ſigne the work was done; for ſaid Chriſt<note n="(w)" place="margin">John 16.7.</note> 
               <hi>except I go away, the Comforter cannot come.</hi> I ſay it's a ſign Jeſus Chriſt hath finiſhed the work; for do you thinke the Lord would have ſent his Goſpel to men to tel men, or his ſpirit to aſſure men it was done, if it had not been done, and thus much now concerning the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of the point.</p>
            <p>Before I come to the application of the Doctrine, give me leave to anſwer one or two objections.</p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Object.</hi> The firſt objection is this; <hi>If Jeſus Chriſt had finiſhed the worke of mens Redemption and of mens Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation upon earth, why then are men commanded to worke out their owne ſalvation, if the work be already done? what need the debtor be exhorted to pay, if the ſurety have alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy paid for him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The Apoſtles meaning in exhorting men to work out their ſalvation, is this, <hi>That they ſhould perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vere in the way they did profeſſe, &amp; not fall from the truth;</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:117698:17"/>or as the Greek word <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> ſignifies a wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king through, and ſo it's to be underſtood for a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſevering work.</p>
            <p>Secondly, when men are called to <hi>doing,</hi> or to <hi>worke,</hi> they are not called to do that they might have life, or be juſtified; but men are called to do, becauſe they are<note n="(x)" place="margin">Tit. 3.5, 6.</note> juſtified, and becauſe they are ſaved, <hi>i. e.</hi> in a ſtate of ſalvation, becauſe they have life, and not that they may have it; for the Lord never in the Scripture maketh works the cauſe of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> or the cauſe of <hi>Salvation:</hi> no, it is a <hi>ſubſequent,</hi> and an <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect,</hi> and that which followes a mans juſtification, or that which floweth from a juſtified perſon. For here is the difference between works, as they are done un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a covenant of workes, and under a covenant of grace; works when they are done under a covenant of works, they are done to ſeek juſtification &amp; ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; they are done to work righteouſneſs for man to keepe him out of hell: But workes done under the covenant of grace, they are done out of<note n="(y)" place="margin">2 Cor. 5.14</note> love to Chriſt, done to the<note n="(z)" place="margin">1 Cor. 10.31.</note> glory of God, done to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe that we are<note n="(a)" place="margin">Col. 3.1.</note> Chriſtians, and that we are<note n="(b)" place="margin">John 8.31. and 15.8.</note> Chriſts Diſciples, and ſo to doe works as the cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of grace requires workes, as the duty of Chriſtians; but to doe <hi>workes</hi> as the covenant of workes requires <hi>workes,</hi> either upon paine of damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, or upon promiſe of ſalvation, this is to be ſhun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned by Chriſtians.</p>
            <p n="2">2 <hi>Object.</hi> The ſecond Objection: It is true as you ſay, that Jeſus Chriſt hath glorified the Father, and finiſhed the worke of mens <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Salvation,</hi> but you have not ſhewed upon what grounds the Lord did this; peradventure he might do it upon
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117698:18"/>ſome grounds that were not advantagious to us. There were two maine grounds moved him to do this, his love and affection to men was one, and the great neceſſity of men was the <hi>other.</hi> Upon theſe two grounds Jeſus Chriſt came forth from heaven, to worke this worke.</p>
            <p n="1">1 Firſt, it was his <hi>love</hi> and <hi>affection</hi> unto men, the heart of Jeſus Chriſt was towards men upon earth (you may reade) as ſoone as ever they were made; yea Jeſus Chriſt his delight was with them. In the eighth of the <hi>Proverbs,</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>My delights were with the children of men.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 8.31.</note> If his delight was ſo, then much more was it, when the time of their <hi>redemption</hi> drew near, and moſt of all ſince he ſuffered. If <hi>Jacobs</hi> love were ſo great, when he firſt ſaw <hi>Rachell,</hi> how much more did his heart go out to her, when that ſhe was neete to be his wife? If Jeſus Chriſts heart went out, when he firſt ſaw men upon earth, how much more went his heart out towards them,<note place="margin">John 15.13. Gal. 2.20.</note> when the time was come to be married to them. This doubtleſſe was the firſt and maine cauſe why Chriſt did worke this worke of <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>Salvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> was mens <hi>neceſsity,</hi> thi did move Chriſt to do it; there was indeed a neceſſity for Chriſt to come to worke this worke; for had there been any other way, doubtleſſe that way would have been ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken; the Father would never have loſt ſuch a deare Sonne; if there could have been any other means of ſaving men without him: No, he would never have parted with ſuch a companion, that he had ſo much content and comfort in, if Angels might have done the worke; but he looked upon his right hand, and upon his left hand, and there was no <hi>helper.</hi> Then
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117698:18"/>ſayes God, <hi>My owne right hand, or my</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">Iſa. 63.5.</note> 
               <hi>arme wrought ſalvation.</hi> That is, my<note n="(d)" place="margin">Iſa. 53.1. Luke 1.51.</note> Sonne Jeſus Chriſt, he wrought ſalvation. If you underſtand this Text in a ſpirituall ſenſe. Thus having removed the two objections, now I come to the uſes of this point; I ſhall make but three uſes of it, and then conclude; remember the obſervation, <hi>The buſineſse of Ieſus Chriſt upon earth, was to glorifie his Father, and to worke the worke of mens redemption, and the worke of mens ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation; and this buſineſſe he hath finiſhed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>Uſe.</hi> The firſt uſe is a uſe of great incouragement unto ſinfull men: Is the work of mens <hi>Redemption</hi> already fulfilled, finiſhed and already wrought; O what great incouragement is this unto you that are ſinfull, and that are ungodly men; it is incourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment unto you that cannot worke, here is a worke already wrought for you, it is wrought to your hand. I may ſay to you, as it was ſaid in the Goſpell to the men that were invited to the Feaſt, <hi>Loe all is ready,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 22.4.</note> 
               <hi>come,</hi> I tell you here is all ready; here is the work of <hi>redemption</hi> and <hi>ſalvation</hi> wrought; every thing is prepared, come; <hi>The Spirit ſaith, come, the Bride ſaith come, the ſaints ſay come, the Goſpell ſaith come,</hi> every thing ſaith come; Oh come, here is great incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement for you to come. I beſeech you heare, without doubt there be this day, in this place, many ſinners, and many that ſtand in great need of Jeſus Chriſt; here be many poore ſoules that ſtand looking, they cannot tell which way to go, but like a boule, the leaſt thing that toucheth it, will make it turne this way or that way; you are looking which way you ſhall be ſaved; ſome men are great and groſſe ſinners, men that delight in ſinne, and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117698:19"/>ſport in the day, and make it their whole buſineſie to <hi>diſhonour</hi> God, as Chriſt made it his buſineſſe to <hi>honour</hi> him. Well, what ſhall I ſay to you; I deſire to open the gate of Gods grace, and God open you hearts that you may heare what he ſaith unto you the door of his mercy is open to you already;<note place="margin">Encouragements for ſinners to come into Chriſt and to believe on his grace. <hi>1</hi> Encour.</note> and that I may incourage you to come in, I will give you foure or five inducements and motives.</p>
            <p>The firſt is this, That God gave this worke to Chriſt to do, <hi>The worke</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>which thou gaveſt me to do;</hi> note, that God the Father had his hand in this worke of mans <hi>redemption</hi> and <hi>ſalvation,</hi> and it could not have been effected, but that God was willing to have it effected in this manner. This in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement, that God did put Chriſt to doe this worke, is a ſpeciall <hi>intentive</hi> and <hi>motive</hi> to you to believe; for had Chriſt done this worke without his Fathers approbation, you might have queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned whether he would have accepted of it; but it being done by his appointment, and by order from him, he muſt needs accept of it.</p>
            <p>Secondly conſider this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>2</hi> Encour.</note> that there is nothing of the worke left undone; no, the Lord hath not left ſo much as a ſtone for you to turne, not one thing for you to do: Chriſt tels you here, <hi>he hath finiſhed the worke,</hi> and you may believe it, for he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver undertake or begin a <hi>buſineſſe</hi> or <hi>worke,</hi> and not go through it. Oh that you had hearts to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve this, that Chriſt hath done all, and that there is nothing of that worke left for you to do.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj.</hi> But you wil ſay, by your favour Sir, he hath not done all, for he requires I ſhould <hi>believe</hi> and <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent,</hi> and turne from my ſinnes, and be obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117698:19"/>unto him; and ſurely he hath thereby put enough of work upon me, and more then I am able to do.</p>
            <p>O poor ſoules (hearken to this) Jeſus Chriſt hath not left the worke of <hi>beliveing, repenting, turning from ſinne,</hi> or <hi>obeying</hi> upon you, but he hath that worke ſtill to do in you; he hath done one worke in his perſon, and now he hath another worke to do by his Spirit, and Jeſus Chriſt he looks upon that worke as belonging to him. Marke how he ſpake (of calling ſinners) in <hi>John</hi> 4.4.<note place="margin">John. 4.4.</note> 
               <hi>He muſt needs go, through Samaria.</hi> And why? becauſe he was to call (and to work faith in) ſome of the poore Samari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans, this he makes his worke. So in <hi>John</hi> 10.16.<note place="margin">John 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>Other ſheep I have</hi> (ſaish he) <hi>that are not of this fold, them alſo I muſt bring (into the fold;)</hi> he ſaith not, there are other ſheep, and I muſt go and ſend <hi>ſhepherds</hi> to drive them home, or ſend dogs after them, to courſe them home; no, but I muſt go <hi>ſeeke them,</hi> and <hi>bring them</hi> home; he puts a <hi>me oportet, (I muſt)</hi> up on it. Marke this, that as Chriſt hath per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected the <hi>worke</hi> of <hi>redemption</hi> in his owne perſon, ſo he will alſo create the worke of <hi>ſanctification</hi> in your perſons, as he did that worke in his owne fleſh, ſo he will do the other in your fleſh. This is the <hi>tenour</hi> of the <hi>Covenant of grace, I will do all,</hi> yea this is the nature of it, <hi>I will do all freely;</hi> God in the Covenant of grace doth no condition from me, but what he promiſed to worke in men. It is true, you muſt <hi>believe,</hi> and <hi>repent</hi> before you can go to heaven, but the Lord undertakes this worke himſelf. For ſaith the Lord,<note n="(d)" place="margin">Heb. 8.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>I will put my Law into their mindes, and write them in their hearts.</hi> That is,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117698:20"/>he will teach them to <hi>know</hi> him, <hi>believe</hi> in him, and to be obedient to him, he doth not ſay in the Covenant of grace, do theſe things your ſelves, but he ſaith, <hi>I will</hi>
               <note n="(e)" place="margin">
                  <hi>See</hi> Jer. 32.40. Pſa. 54.13. Math. 12.21. Joh. 6<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4 45. Heb. 10.16.</note> 
               <hi>worke all your works in you, and for you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>I, but then Sir you will ſay, we muſt have theſe things wrought in us before we goe to Heaven.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Very true, you muſt have them wrought in you, but how, and by whom? Not by any ſtrength of your owne, but you are to goe to the <hi>Lord,</hi> and ſay unto him, <hi>Lord,</hi> thou requireſt <hi>knowledge, faith, repentance,</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> of me, and thou ſayſt no <hi>ignorant perſon, unbeliever,</hi> or <hi>impenitent</hi> perſon ſhall goe to Heaven, Lord, if thou wilt not worke this <hi>knowledge, faith, repentance,</hi> and <hi>obedience</hi> in me, thou hadſt as good never have borne my ſinnes, Lord Jeſus, ſeeing thou haſt wrought <hi>Redemption</hi> and <hi>ſalvation</hi> for me, now worke <hi>Sanctification</hi> in me, thou haſt done the worke out of me, and for me, now come, and worke the worke in me; Sue out the Covenant of grace, and if thou haſt no meanes to ſue by, then ſue by <hi>forma pauperis,</hi> as men uſe to doe that wants money, you know they come with a white paper, and ſue thereby and are heard, ſo you <hi>want knowledge, faith, ſtrength, power,</hi> and <hi>holineſſe,</hi> ſue in that way; take the promiſes of the Lord, and goe with them as tickets, and ſay, Lord, is not this thy hand? and is not this thy pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe? is not this thy writing? haſt not thou or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained this? for me to take hold on, <hi>Lord;</hi> I bring thine own <hi>tickets</hi> to thee, Lord, doe for me, as thou haſt ſaid, It is thy promiſe, thou wilt open the <hi>blind eyes,</hi> ſtand to thy word, thou haſt ſaid thou wilt
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:117698:20"/>worke <hi>faith,</hi> here comes a poore unbelieving, at leaſt a doubting ſinner to thee; I will try whether thou wilt worke faith in me, goe and put the Lord to his promiſe, and thou ſhalt ſee he will never deny his owne hand-writing, nor his owne word, well, there be two incouragements for you.</p>
            <p>The third incouragement (I pray you conſider it well) It is the ſpeciall will of the Lord that you ſhould believe,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> and will not you doe his ſpeciall will; If the Lord command you to <hi>pray,</hi> or com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand you to <hi>faſt,</hi> or <hi>mourne,</hi> you will doe that worke, but this is <hi>the worke,</hi> or the moſt accepta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worke to God. Marke;<note place="margin">John 16.28.29.</note> When one came to Chriſt, and asked him, <hi>What ſhall we doe to worke the works of God, Ieſus anſwered, and ſaid unto him, this is the workes (or the worke that will be wel-pleaſing to God,) to believe on him whom of God he hath ſent,</hi> As if Chriſt had ſaid unto him, If thou wilt be doing, or will pleaſe my Father by working, I tell thee, there is no ſuch way as by believing in me.</p>
            <p>The fourth <hi>encouragement</hi> is this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>4.</hi> Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> a man that hath no <hi>worke</hi> at all in him, no <hi>performances,</hi> no <hi>qualifications,</hi> nor preparations, yet ſuch a one hath free liberty to come to the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, yea, as free as any other man whatſoever, I tell you, <hi>Whoremaſters, drunkards,</hi> and <hi>ſwearers,</hi> that have diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>honoured God as much as you could diſhonour <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>the Lord ſpeake this to your heart,</hi> here is an open doore, here is rich grace, and free grace, the heart of Christ is as much towards you as any other ſinners; If there be any plea for any ſinner, there is a plea for this ſort of ſinner, yea, ſuch a one may ſay, <hi>Lord, then cameſt not to call the rightecus, but ſinners to
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117698:21"/>repentance,</hi> never was there any greater ſinner then I, thou cameſt there to call Publicans, and Harlots, ſuch a wicked wretch have I been for many yeares, <hi>Lord</hi> receive me, I am now willing to come to thee, doe not caſt me away, for thou haſt<note n="(g)" place="margin">
                  <hi>Job. 6.37</hi> The greek is <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. I will not, not, caſt out, out.</note> ſaid, <hi>thou wilt in no wiſe caſt out ſuch a one,</hi> What think you will Chriſt ſay to ſuch a one? Surely this, thou art welcome, come poore ſinner, thou art heartily wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come. I have grace for thee, and I am contented to beſtow it freely on thee, I have called thee, and thou art come, hearken what I ſay unto thee<note n="(h)" place="margin">Luke 15.4.</note> 
               <hi>There was a certaine man had a hundred ſheep, and when he had loſt one,</hi> he left the reſt, and went to ſeek that which was loſt; thou art that ſheep which waſt loſt but now art found.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Oh but another may ſay, I, Chriſt calls</hi> ſinners <hi>and</hi> Publicans, <hi>and accepts of ſuch; but I feare I am a</hi> Phariſee,<note place="margin">John 7 37, 38. <hi>with</hi> Acts 2.37, 38.</note> 
               <hi>a</hi> form all Profeſſor, <hi>yea, a Hypocrite, where doth he call ſuch, or where is there any promiſe made to ſuch?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Put the caſe you be ſuch, (though you do but thinke it) yet you read of a call to ſuch, a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe to ſuch, and of the converſion of ſuch, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare <hi>Iohn</hi> 7.37, 38. with <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37, 38.</p>
            <p>The fifth <hi>incouragement</hi> is this, that the greater ſinners you are, when you come to believe in Chriſt, the more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>honour Chriſt hath from you; If a man man that is not a great and common <hi>ſinner,</hi> be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted, alas, there is no talke of him, this mans was looked on as a good morrall man before, a man that made ſome ſhew of Religion, a man that went after Sermons, and one that had ſome good will to good men, and good things. Before ſuch
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117698:21"/>an one was never looked upon as a <hi>drunkard, Swearer,</hi> and the like, I ſay this man is converted, and no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice taken of him. But as when a Monſter is borne the Country rings of him, ſo when a monſtrous and great ſinner is borne againe, when a man that hath been a ring leader of others in wickedneſſe, and that hath lead and haled others in the way to hell, and gone downe the hill himſelfe, as faſt as ever he could to his owne damnation, I ſay when ſuch a man is drawn out of his wicked and miſerable condition, and brought to Chriſt, what will others they ſay, Oh did you heare the newes! what newes? Such a man, ſuch a great <hi>ſinner</hi> that was given for loſt is become a <hi>Saint,</hi> ſuch a man that was ſo great an <hi>enemy</hi> to Religion is now converted. Such a <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecutor</hi> is become a zealous <hi>Profeſſor.</hi> Is it ſo? yes, there is no man in the Country forward for Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on as he is, all the Country will ring of ſuch a ſinners converſion, hearken ſinner, wouldſt thou not have the name of God ring through Heaven, and Earth at thy converſion, wouldſt thou not have God glorified, and thy owne ſoule ſaved, this day there would be joy in Heaven, and glory to God on Earth, if thou wouldſt yield to come in to Chriſt, and to be converted: The Lord ſay <hi>Amen</hi> to it.</p>
            <p>The fifth <hi>encouragement</hi> is this,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>5.</hi> Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> Chriſt hath ſpare grace for you. thats another, alas, what ſhall this gracious charitable King do with all his grace?<note place="margin">The Lord hath greateſt glory from the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt ſinner when he is converted.</note> what ſhall he doe with ſo much gold lying by him, if poore diſtreſſed people doe not come in to fetch it, what ſhall Chriſt doe with all his merits, and ſufferings, (which he hath in ſtore ſtill to be given out to ſinners) if ſinners who want it, will not have
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117698:22"/>it; <hi>Marke</hi> what I ſay to you, if ſo many ſinners, as are here this day, did come to him, he hath grace enough for them and ſo many to morrow, and ſo every day, till the day of the <hi>Reſurrection,</hi> yet Chriſt hath grace enough for them all, will you leane ſuch ſtock of grace in his hands, and not get it, ſince he hath prepared it for you. My beloved, ſuppoſe a man had a ſonne, to whom he had given all his eſtate, this ſonne alſo is very rich of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, and there were a poore woman, that this Sonne hath a minde to make his wife, he comes to her, and ſaith, <hi>woman,</hi> my heart and affections are gone out towards thee, to take thee, and to make my wife, wilt thou accept of me, ſhe refuſeing, he preſſes and woes her further, and ſaith, why, doſt not thou conſider what a rich father I have? he hath made all his eſtate <hi>over</hi> to me, conſidereſt thou not alſo what <hi>wealth</hi> and <hi>riches</hi> I have, doe but heare me, and condiſcend to my requeſt, and ſay I wll have thee for my husband, and all this ſhall be thine; Thus ſaith Jeſus Chriſt to a ſinner, poore ſinner, heareſt thou not what my <hi>father</hi> hath given me, and heareſt thou not what an <hi>heire</hi> I am, doe thou but own me, and take my yoake upon thee, and be my <hi>Diſciple,</hi> and all this will I give thee; As the Devill offered faigned all the world to Jeſus Chriſt, if he would ſubmit to him: So Jeſus Chriſt offers really all the world to a poore ſinner, if he will come in, and ſubmit to him. <hi>Againe,</hi> ſuppoſe a rich man did ſtand in a publique place, among a multitude of poore, and ſhould ſay unto them, you poore, whatſoever you are; without reſpect of perſons, come to me, I will beſtow what you want upon
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117698:22"/>you, whether <hi>money,</hi> or <hi>meat,</hi> or cloathes, all theſe I have ready for you, come, and receive them, vvhat would not theſe poore people thinke you, come to him, nay, would they not crowde in upon him; Why thus ſaith Jeſus Chriſt to poore ſinners, I have grace enough to beſtow upon you, come in, and you ſhall be welcome; come, and looke, what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever you want, I will beſtow it upon you, now what ſtands in thy way oh thou poore ſinner? or what hinders thee to come in?</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Oh Sir! this ſtands in my way, though I know Chriſt hath finiſhed the worke of mens redemption, and of mens ſalvation, yet I doe not know whether he hath finiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed it for me?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Hearken my beloved, what ground have you to make a plea againſt your ſelves, he hath done it for<note n="(i)" place="margin">Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.8. 1 Tim. 1.15.</note> 
               <hi>ſinners,</hi> for the<note n="(k)" place="margin">Rom. 5.6.</note> 
               <hi>ungodly,</hi> for<note n="(l)" place="margin">Pſal. 68.18.</note> 
               <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells,</hi> for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="(m)" place="margin">John 6.51.</note> 
               <hi>world,</hi> you are a <hi>ſinner,</hi> you are one of the <hi>ungodly,</hi> one of the <hi>world,</hi> what plea can you make againſt this why object you ſuch an objection againſt your ſelves? If a pardon be ſent from a Prince to a company of Priſoners, and the Meſſenger ſaith unto them in generall, here is a Pardon for you, from my Prince for what you have done againſt him, come, accept of it and you ſhall be free. Now if one ſhould aske, is the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don for me? and another queſtion is the Pardon for me? he would anſwer. It is for you that are Pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners, without acception, if you accept of it. A Pardon is now ſent unto you, that are finfull men and women, who are Priſoners under the power of Satan, and ſinne; I ſay to you all, the Lord Jeſus hath ſent forth his pardon, which runs thus; <hi>I the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117698:23"/>Lord Ieſus, the Son of God, and the Saviour of ſinners, out of my free grace</hi> and mercy, rich love, and pity am willing to pardon, and forgive the ſinnes and tranſgreſſions of you all; and this I will doe really, if you will come in, and lay hold of this pardon, and of my righteouſneſſe. Will a ſinner now ſay, doth Jeſus Chriſt meane me, ſeeing he ſaith, <hi>who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever comes unto me: I will in no wiſe caſt him out: and whoſoever believes on me he ſhall be pardoned, and ſaved.</hi> This word whoſoever comprehends all, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes none, therefore object not againſt your ſelves; neither refuſe your owne ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>Oh! but though Chriſt invites all and makes promiſes to all that doe come, yet he intends not that all ſhould be made partakers thereof.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ. My beloved,</hi> thinke you that Chriſts inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, and his expreſſion are not one as reall as ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. I tell you (and you may believe) that he intends to pardon all, and to ſave all, as he expreſs<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth it. He ſaith not the words only, but his heart is ſo alſo. But marke it well (and miſtake me not) I doe not meane that he ſaith abſoluely, <hi>I'le pardon all, and ſave all,</hi> and no more, oh no; but he ſpeaks conditionally, <hi>I'le pardon you all, and ſave you all,</hi> if you believe on me and accept of my pardon.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Obj. But alas he were as good never tender me a pardon, nor make me a promiſe, upon thoſe tearmes, for of my ſelfe I cannot believe, nor receive his pardon and grace.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Its true, of your ſelves you cannot believe, nor receive his pardon, and grace, though tendred to you: yet as I ſaid before, cry upon him to give you <hi>eyes</hi> to ſee him, and his grace, and <hi>feete</hi> to come to him, and hands to take hold upon his merits, and
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117698:23"/>righteouſneſſe. He promiſeth largely and freely, <hi>peradventure,</hi> now while the word is ſpeaking, God will be working theſe things in you.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But he doth not give this grace to, (nor worke this grace in) all, but to few, therefore doe I feare, leaſt I ſhould not be one of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Though he doth not give grace to all, (for he hath not tyed himſelf ſo to doe, neither is the cauſe in God why men want grace, for he gave ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiently at firſt) yet you are bound to ſeek, and the promiſe is made to Seekers, nay I may ſpeake more, the Lord is found of ſome that ſeeke him not.<note place="margin">Prov. 18.4. Jer. 29.13. Rom. 10.20. Ezek. 34.6.11.12.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But peradventure another here, may further object and ſay, I have long ſought, and I am even weary of ſeeking: yea, I am ready to conclude, that if I had belong'd to God, I ſhould have found grace in his ſight ere now.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Oh deare ſoules, conclude nothing, neither againſt your ſelves, nor againſt the Lord, for he hath ſought you longer then you ſought him. And you have not yet been thirtie-eight years waiting at the waters (<hi>Chriſts Ordinances</hi>) as that weak and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>potent man. Oh ſoule! peradventure the Lord is now asking thee as he did this man;<note place="margin">John 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> 
               <hi>Wilt thou be made whole?</hi> If he be ſo, make him anſwer, and ſay, <hi>Lord I am weake, but yet waiting, oh help me, and heale me Lord.</hi> Thus much for the firſt uſe.</p>
            <p>Seeing Chriſt hath glorified his Father,<note place="margin">Uſe. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> and fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed the worke of mens Redemption, and Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, this then directs, and teaches men what they ſhould not doe, and alſo what they ſhould doe. Firſt, what they ſhould not doe.</p>
            <p>In the firſt place,<note place="margin">Firſt.</note> they ſhould not goe about to worke their owne Redemption and Salvation
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:117698:24"/>againe, for if Chriſt hath wrought it already, then its in vaine, (yea, its <hi>ignorance,</hi> and <hi>folly</hi>) to think of doing any thing towards your owne <hi>Inſtification,</hi> and <hi>ſalvation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Sure there be none that thinke to doe any thing for, and towards their juſtification and ſalvation, unleſſe they be Papiſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw,</hi> Oh yes, there be many beſides <hi>Papiſts,</hi> thot doe ſo, for doe but aske many <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> how they thinke to be juſtified and ſaved? they will tell you by their good works, and well-doing, If we doe well (ſay they) we ſhall have well, and if we doe ill, we ſhall have accordingly. Yea, this is apparent in men, both living; and dying. In their life time they will ſay, if we can but keep the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandements, <hi>viz.</hi> to love God above all, and our Neighbours as our ſelves, then we hope it will goe well with us. Then at their death they thinke that to build an <hi>Hoſpitall,</hi> (or to doe ſome ſuch charita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worke,) will ſave their ſoules. <hi>Marke this,</hi> it is eaſier to doe good works, then to undoe our ſelves from them, and <hi>to have no confidence in them,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 3.3.</note> and to be able to ſay, as the Apoſtle ſaid, in him (<hi>i.e.</hi> Chriſt) I deſire to be found, not having my owne righteouſneſs, <hi>v.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secondly.</note> on the other hand, men ſhould not <hi>reſt</hi> and <hi>ſit</hi> ſtill, and content themſelves with this bare notion, that Chriſt came to <hi>redeeme</hi> to and <hi>ſave</hi> ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners; and that if he died for them, then they ſhall be ſaved. Oh! what are you the better that he dyed for ſinners, unleſſe you know the death of Chriſt in the worth and efficacy of it, and unleſs you have it apply'd it to your ſelves in particular, and be able
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117698:24"/>upon good grounds to ſay as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid, <hi>Chriſt came in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the world to ſave ſinners of whom I am chief:</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1.13. Gal. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>and Chriſt loved me and gave ſatisfaction for me,</hi> this particular faith you ſtand in need of.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>I do beleeve that he dyed for me in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> But upon what ground do you beleeve it? what promiſe have you to build your faith upon: there is a kind of<note n="*" place="margin">Luk. 8.12. Act. 8.13.</note> 
               <hi>Hyſtoricall beleeving,</hi> or aſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting unto this truth that Chriſt died for ſinners, which is not a <hi>lively</hi> but a <hi>dead</hi> faith, which may ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be called a <hi>fancy</hi> then a <hi>faith,</hi> this is but a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceit that ariſes in your hearts, like the dreame of a ſleeping man, alas! alas! be not deceived for if e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one did beleeve that doth ſay he doth beleeve, the numbers of beleevers would be <hi>far greater.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>I am ſure my faith is as good as moſt mens faith.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> I tell you moſt mens faith is not worth a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, for it is but <hi>Copper faith, and carnall faith,</hi> a faith that they had, they know not how, nor they know not when ſuch a faith as they wil pawne for a penny.<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.1. Act. 15.9. Eph.</note> There is a great deale of difference betweene your <hi>faith</hi> and the <hi>faith</hi> of the godly, for your faith (I meane you that are (as the moſt are) <hi>carnall</hi>) is not a faith begotten and wrought by the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and <hi>ſpirit:</hi> it is not a <hi>precious purifying, powerfull working ſoule-humbling</hi> faith: (ſuch as is the faith com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended in the Seriptures) and ſuch a faith as does undoe you, and ſtrip you naked of all you have. This is the faith of the godly, which moſt want, (and which is worſe), are not ſenſible that they want it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Take heed of making your faith to be the
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:117698:25"/>cauſe of your Juſtification: For thereby <hi>you</hi> may miſſe it as well as <hi>others</hi> miſſ'd it, by making their works the cauſe. <hi>Note,</hi> that faith is but the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and <hi>meanes,</hi> whereby you do <hi>apprehend</hi> and enjoy your <hi>iuſtification.</hi> Chriſt is your <hi>righteouſneſſe,</hi> and by <hi>him,</hi> and his <hi>death, ſufferings,</hi> you are juſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed:<note place="margin">2 Cor. 5.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>9. Rom. 8.33.</note> yea and that truly and really too (I meane vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually in Chriſt, and before God) before you do be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But doth not the Act of beleeving iuſtifie men?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 4.6.3. Gal. 3.6.</note> for it is ſaid of <hi>Abraham</hi> that his faith was rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koned to him for righteouſneſſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> 1. Its true, that <hi>Abrahams faith</hi> was reckoned to him for righteouſneſſe. But mark, when was that reckoned to him, and what was it that he did be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeve? Do but read <hi>Gen.</hi> 15.6. where this Text is firſt found in Scripture, and you will find there, that this beleeving of his was the beleeving the promiſe concerning the giving of <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and the multiplying of his ſeed:<note place="margin">Gen. 12.3. &amp; 13.3.9. &amp; 14.19.</note> and this Promiſe was made a long time after his firſt beleeving. <hi>Gen.</hi> 12.3.3. &amp; 13.3, 9, &amp; 14.19. Alſo the Apoſtle <hi>Jamee</hi> apply's this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion to <hi>Abrahams</hi> work, even to the offering up of <hi>Iſaac. Jam.</hi> 2.21. &amp; 23.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſame expreſſion is uſed of <hi>Phinehas</hi> for kil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cozby.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 206.13.</note> 
               <hi>That</hi> (ſaith the Text) <hi>was coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted unto him for righteouſneſſe,</hi> will any now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude from hence, that the killing of theſe two <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleane</hi> perſons was the cauſe of <hi>Phineas</hi> juſtification from ſinne? No; the meaning of it is this, that this Act did teſtifie his faith and righteouſneſſe, and God did reckon and account it as a righteous <hi>Act.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But the Scripture is cleare that men are iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied by faith, and by beleoving.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:117698:25"/>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> So the Scripture is cleare, that men are juſtified by<note n="(a)" place="margin">Iam. 2.2.24, 25.</note> Works &amp; by<note n="(b)" place="margin">Mat. 12.3 Luk. 18 14.</note> Words But you are to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand in what ſenſe men are juſtified by theſe. Mark therefore. By<note n="(c)" place="margin">Gal. 2.1 Rom. 3.24.1 Cor. 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Chriſt his <hi>death, ſufferings,</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,</hi> men are really, and virtually juſtified. By faith men are <hi>perſonally,</hi> and <hi>apprehenſively</hi> juſtified, and by Works and Words, men are <hi>decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratively</hi> juſtified: In the first ſenſe men are justified before <hi>God,</hi> in the ſecond ſenſe they are justified in their own conſciences, and in the third ſenſe, they are justified before men.</p>
            <p>So having directed you what you ſhould take heed of, and not do: I come in the next place to ſhew you, and direct you what you ſhould do. I ſhall give you but five directions and thoſe in ſhort.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Labour to eve all that Chriſt hath done, as done for <hi>others, and not</hi> for <hi>himſelfe;</hi> for Chriſt was not like the High Prieſt under the Law,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.27.</note> that was to <hi>offer, firſt for his owne ſins, and then for the ſins of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple:</hi> No, he had no ſinne of his owne to ſuffer for (as I ſhewed before) therefore what ever he did, &amp; ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fered, he did &amp; ſuffered the ſame as a <hi>ſurety &amp; Saviour.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Object I <hi>know that Chriſt dyed for others, and not for himſelfe, but then it was for his elect, I feare I am not one of them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Thou art not to enquire after (or once to queſtion) thy election, till thou doſt firſt believe: And ſo the Apoſtle teacheth; <hi>Say not in thy heart,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Rom. 60.1</note> 
               <hi>who ſhall aſcend into Heaven, that is, to bring Christ from a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove:</hi> Or, <hi>who ſhall aſcend into the deepe? that is, to bring up Chriſt againe from the dead</hi> (i.e. look neither upon <hi>Election</hi> nor <hi>preterition,</hi> but look upon the word of
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117698:26"/>faith, which is preached to thee, and which com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands thee to beleeve.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly, Stay not from Chriſt till you ſet and find humiliation, preparations, and qualifications in your ſelves:</hi> for this in a ſence is either to look upon Chriſts <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> as not ſufficient, or elſe to look upon Chriſt as unwilling to make you partakers of it, unleſſe you bring ſomewhat in <hi>lieu</hi> of it, at leaſt till you are fitted for it you cannot have it. Conſider (I pray you) where? and from whom can you have that humiliation, preparation, and qualfication, unleſſe it be from Chriſt, God the Father ſaith <hi>that he will give him</hi> (i e. <hi>Chriſt) for a Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant unto the people,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eſa. 42 6.7.</note> 
               <hi>to open the eyes of the blind, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here you ſee Chriſt <hi>muſt open the eyes of the blind</hi> before they can ſee. So Chriſt himſelfe ſaith, <hi>without me ye can do nothing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 15.5.</note> if men can do nothing without Chriſt, why then ſhould they think to fit themſelves for him.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>Becauſe that thoſe that are ſo fitted and humbled are called to Christ, and have the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe belonging unto them.</hi> As Christ ſaith, <hi>Ho e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one that thirſleth, come ye to the waters:</hi> and in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother place, <hi>Come unto me all yee that are weary and heavy laden and I will eaſe you.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> You and many others doubtleſſe have been much <hi>miſtaken</hi> in thoſe, and ſuch Scriptures, for the meaning is not that Christ inviteth, and maketh pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe only to ſuch that are <hi>thirſty heavy laden,</hi> &amp;c. Though it be true that he invites thoſe, and makes promiſes unto ſuch in a more <hi>ſpeciall</hi> manner, yet not excluding others.</p>
            <p>As a <hi>Phiſitian</hi> that comes to two <hi>Patients</hi> to cure
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:117698:26"/>them both, yet if he ſee the <hi>one</hi> in greater paint and torment then the <hi>other,</hi> he will take him in hand be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the other, but not him only: for he will cure the other, alſo that paradventure may be leſſe ſencible, yea altogether ſenceleſſe of his diſeaſe or wound.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But yet me thinks a man that is not wounded, will never deſire to goe to the Phiſitiam, nor have the Phiſitian come to him. So a ſinner that is not fenſible of his ſinnes will not goe to Chriſt, neither will hee bee willing that I ſhould come to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Though poore ſenceles ſinners will not go to Chriſt nor deſire their <hi>Phiſitian</hi> Chriſt to come unto them, yet Chriſt knowing their <hi>want</hi> and <hi>danger</hi> will come to them as he went to the <hi>Samaritans</hi> &amp; others.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But he ſaith, he is come to ſeek and to ſave that which is loſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> Very true, but he doth not ſay thoſe that did ſee themſelves loſt (thoſe I grant he comes more ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to ſeek heere he means)<note place="margin">See Luk. 19 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> with Mat. 9.11.1.</note> but to thoſe that were the greateſt ſinners, and loſt in the eyes of others, as the <hi>Publicans</hi> and <hi>Harlots</hi> were in the apprehenſions of the <hi>Iews:</hi> This is the true meaning of that <hi>Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thirdly.</note> Diſtinguiſh between Chriſts work of <hi>Redemption</hi> that he hath done without men in his own perſon, by <hi>obedience,</hi> &amp; the other w<hi rend="sup">c</hi>h. he works in men by his ſpirit. Obſerve that men are not to look for any thing in themſelves either before beleeving. or after, as cauſing juſtification. <hi>For Iuſtification is Gods reckoning thoſe that were ſinners to be no ſinners, or thoſe that were Debtors no Debtors,</hi> and this through Chriſt &amp; upon his account. <hi>But ſanctification is a putting forth of aholy and heavenly power, to the changing of mens carnall
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:117698:27"/>principles, and making them ſpirituall: and to the purging of mens filthyneſſe, and making them cleane.</hi> So that the Apostle aſcribes <hi>Iuſtification</hi> to the name <hi>righteouſneſſe</hi> of Christ and <hi>ſanctification</hi> to the ſpirit or Christ.<note place="margin">1 Co. 11.</note> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Fourthly.</note> When you come to Christ to look for <hi>juſtification</hi> (or to be justified) then you must come as <hi>ſinners,</hi> and not as <hi>Saints.</hi> As the Apostle ſaith: <hi>If while we ſeck to be juſtified by Chriſt we our ſelves alſo are feund ſinners</hi> (that is in the capacity of ſinners.)<note place="margin">Gal. 2.17.</note> For indeed it is improper for a man that is a Saint to come to look for Justification (for he is justified before) unleſſe he comes to have his Justification <hi>cleared</hi> and <hi>renewed</hi> in his own Conſcience. As a man that hath a pardon for his life, may (if his par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don be blurd or broken) get it renewed; yet the renewing of it is not the first grant: ſo Saints may get their pardons <hi>renewed,</hi> and <hi>tranſcribed</hi> in their Conſciences, but yet when they aſk pardon of God, they must conſider, that the former pardon (granted up on Chriſts <hi>reſurrection,</hi> and likevviſe upon the <hi>firſt Act of beleeving</hi>) is recorded in <hi>Heaven.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, Saints, if you looſe your <hi>Evidences,</hi> and vvritings for Heaven committed to you, yet know they are en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolled in the <hi>Court of glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> And lastly, you ſhould get an <hi>experience</hi> of vvhat Christ hath done in his ovvne perſon, in your perſons: I meane, that you ſhould not only have a ſight,<note place="margin">Rom. 5.11.4.5</note> by faith, of the vertue of Chriſts death to justification, but that you likevviſe get a feeling of that vvarme bloud of his, to <hi>comfort</hi> and <hi>chear</hi> up your ſoules. Get experience placed, as the Apostle places it, betvveen <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Hope,</hi> or betvveen <hi>Iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication</hi>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:117698:27"/>and <hi>Salvation.</hi> So much for the ſecond uſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>third</hi> and last <hi>VSE</hi> is of Exhortation unto all (but eſpecially unto you that are called to do the vvork of the Lord) that you would be follovvers of <hi>Ieſus Chriſt.</hi> Here Christ could ſay, <hi>He had finiſhed the work which was given him to do.</hi> But many of you may ſay, that you have not yet begun the vvork, (though you are ready to go to your graves) I vvould exhort you to imitate Christ, for you cannot have a better Example. But before I come to the parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Exhortation, Conſider 3. things.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> That every man hath a work (or his work) to do upon earth. God leaves no man <hi>Idle,</hi> but he turnes all into the Vineyard and gives every man his work:<note place="margin">Mar. 13.34.</note> So ſaith our Saviour in the 13. of <hi>Mark</hi> and the 34. <hi>And he gave to every man his work.</hi> Now I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeech you conſider, that the Lord hath given you ſom <hi>work</hi> to do; you that are <hi>Magiſtrates,</hi> the Lord hath given you ſome <hi>work</hi> to do. The Lord help you to know, what that work is: he hath highly honored you, to cal you to his <hi>work,</hi> he might have left you, as you were, unworthy to have taken his <hi>work</hi> in hand; there is none of you worthy to doe the worke of Jeſus Chriſt; yet he hath ſo farre expreſt his willingneſſe to <hi>exalt</hi> you, to ſee whether you will <hi>exalt</hi> him.<note place="margin">Joh. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.49.</note> You know, Jeſus Chriſt he did very often look upon this work, in the 12. of <hi>John,</hi> and the 49. <hi>verſe I have not ſpoken of myſelfe, but the Father which ſent me, he gave me Commandement, what I ſhould ſay, and what I ſhould ſpeak.</hi> So the <hi>Father</hi> hath given <hi>you a Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> what you ſhould doe; know that there is a work given unto you; that is <hi>the firſt thing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Then the <hi>Second</hi> thing is this, that you have <hi>but a time</hi> to doe this work in; <hi>There is a time</hi>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:117698:28"/>(ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) in the 3 of <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> the firſt) <hi>for every thing under the Sun:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Eol. 3.1.</note> the Lord hath peradventure gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven you a <hi>long time</hi> to do the work, and you have not don is, well, when the Lords <hi>Glaſſe</hi> is run, you muſt be taken away, and the work out of your hands. Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member (you that are in <hi>Authority,</hi>) what befel ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times your <hi>Predeceſſers</hi> that were good men, when they had done their work, they were taken away, you know not but that the Lord hath called you this yeare to do his work, and peradventure after this yeare is out, your time is out, and your Glaſſe run, <hi>therefore</hi> think of that alſo, that <hi>every man hath his time</hi> as well as his work.</p>
            <p>Then <hi>thirdly, every man muſt give an account of his work and Stewardſhip.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thirdly.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Know this that from the greateſt to the ſmaleſt, from the higheſt to the loweſt, you muſt <hi>come and appeare before the Iudgement ſeat of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10.</note> and Chriſt will ſay to one, <hi>You that I have made chiefe Magiſtrate of</hi> London, <hi>what have you don in that yeare of your Office?</hi> and ſay to others,<note place="margin">Act. 26.25.27</note> 
               <hi>you Sheriffs; you Recorder; what have you done?</hi> yea, this muſt be ſpoken particularly to men, is <hi>Paul</hi> ſpake to <hi>Feſtus</hi> and <hi>Agrippa.</hi> (I ſpeak with humility to you, and ſubmiſſion to the will of the Lord,) you will one day be called by your names, <hi>ſuch a man, in ſuch a place, in ſuch an Office, that ruled in ſuch a yeare, what haſt thou done? Thou muſt render an account to me what thou haſt done, how thou haſt improved thy talent, what good thou haſt done in thy place, what glory thou haſt brought to my name, what comfort thou haſt wrought in my peoples hearts, what terrors thou haſt wrought in the hearts of my adverſaries?</hi> In the 20. of the <hi>Revel.</hi> and the 12.<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Revel.</hi> 20.12.</note> There when they are called
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117698:28"/>to <hi>account</hi> of what they have done: you have both ſmall and great ſtanding before God,<note place="margin">Mat. 12.36.</note> many<note n="*" place="margin">As Rom. 14.12.</note> ſuch Scriptures beſides; now conſidering this, that firſt you have a <hi>work</hi> to do,<note place="margin">Hebr. 13.17 1 Pet. 4, 5. &amp;c.</note> and ſecondly you have <hi>but a time</hi> to do that work, and Thirdly that you muſt <hi>give an account</hi> of this work.</p>
            <p>I come to the <hi>exhortation,</hi> (and I beſeech you Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren <hi>beare the word of exhortation;</hi>) The <hi>exhortation</hi> is <hi>this,</hi> to be <hi>followers of Ieſus Chriſt, particularly in glorifying God; for that end,</hi> I ſhall but hold forth, <hi>how</hi> Ieſus Chriſt did his work; and <hi>paralel</hi> your work with his work; and ſhew, you <hi>how</hi> you are to do it; and ſo <hi>conclude.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>firſt</hi> is this, that <hi>Ieſus Chriſt made it his maine deſigne and buſines to glorifie his Father:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Firſt.</note> It was not a <hi>by</hi>-buſineſſe to Christ, <hi>to glorifie the Father,</hi> but his <hi>maine</hi> buſineſſe; <hi>eating</hi> and <hi>drinking,</hi> and <hi>other buſineſſes,</hi> were but <hi>by</hi>-buſineſſes to him: but the <hi>maine</hi> buſineſſe was to <hi>glorifie his Father:</hi> as you may ſee, in the 4. of <hi>Iohn</hi> the 34. ſaith he, <hi>I have meat to eat,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioh. 4.34.</note> 
               <hi>that you know not of, and this is my meat, to doe the will of him that ſent me, and to finiſh his work:</hi> Here he made <hi>Gods</hi> work, <hi>his</hi> deſigne, and his <hi>maine</hi> buſineſſe. You are to imitate Jeſus Christ in this; you are to make it your <hi>deſigne</hi> to <hi>glorifie God,</hi> and to do the work which God hath called you to. Hath the Lord called you into great plares? it must not be your <hi>deſigne</hi> to make your <hi>ſelves</hi> honourable, and to gaine wealth; repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation and the like, to <hi>your ſelves,</hi> and that the people may <hi>look</hi> upon you with esteeme. This is not your <hi>buſineſſe:</hi> your buſineſſe is, to <hi>honour God,</hi> and to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance his people, to rebuke and pull down ſin,<note place="margin">Rom. 13 3.4.</note> and to be a <hi>terrour</hi> to wicked <hi>workers.</hi> Therefore glorifie
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117698:29"/>God as Christ did; and make it your <hi>deſigne</hi> to glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifie him, for <hi>Chriſt</hi> made it Io.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> Luk. 2 42.</note> 
               <hi>Ieſus Chriſt,</hi> as he made it his <hi>deſigne:</hi> ſo he <hi>began in time about his work.</hi> It is ſaid in the <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond</hi> of <hi>Luke,</hi> when he was but <hi>twelve years of age, that he was diſputing amongſt the Doctors.</hi> Some of you may be 12. <hi>and forty,</hi> and yet have <hi>not begun</hi> nor gone about the work of the Lord. You have loſt much time already; now <hi>begin:</hi> peradverture now (yea this day) God looks you ſhould <hi>begin, when will you begin:</hi> Some were called into the <hi>Vineyard at the</hi> 6th. <hi>houre,</hi> and ſome at the 9th. and ſome at the 11th. But it was expected when they had <hi>a call to the Vineyeard,</hi> that they ſhould <hi>then work.</hi> Now you have had a call, in the name of God <hi>begin</hi> the work,<note place="margin">Math. 22.3.</note> delay it not: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the time <hi>you appoint</hi> to go about the Lords work, you may be taken away. <hi>David</hi> for his ſin, though he had an <hi>Intent to build a houſe</hi> to the Lord, yet he was <hi>taken away before</hi> it was built. And <hi>Moſes</hi> was likewiſe taken away, <hi>before</hi> he came into <hi>Canaan;</hi> Be therefore careful to do the work of the Lord; though while God grants you an opportunity,<note place="margin">1 King. 8.19.</note> ſome may do part of the work remaining in the <hi>Wilderneſſe,</hi> yet ſome others may partake of that work in <hi>Canaan.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then <hi>thirdly</hi> Jeſus Chriſt did not onely glorifie God <hi>himſelfe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thirdly.</note> but he was a <hi>means to make others</hi> to glorifie God. Chriſt did not in his owne perſon only, honour his Father, but he was a <hi>mean's that others</hi> might glorify him alſo. For their Maſter Chriſt choſe ſuch Diſciples (the <hi>poore meane Fiſher men</hi>) that would <hi>glorify</hi> him in doing his work: They were not drunken, covetous ſervants, ſuch as did minde <hi>money,</hi> and means more then their
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:117698:29"/>preaching. You great men that keep ſervants, here is a good example for you, Alſo there is a perti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent <hi>inſtance</hi> in <hi>Ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>emiſh</hi> the fifth Chapter, and the 10. and 15. verſes, (where ſaith he) I <hi>likewiſe, and my brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Neh. 5.10.15</note> 
               <hi>and my ſervants might exact of them mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, and corne, I pray you let us leave off this Uſu y.</hi> So in the 15. verſe, you finde his <hi>ſervants here, not as the former Governors ſervants, that to e rule ever the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple; but why ſo; Marke, in the next words, becauſe of the feare of God. Get ſervants</hi> (like his) that feare God; and by that meanes, you will cleare your ſelves from that <hi>odium,</hi> caſt upon many Gentlemen, that if the Maſter will not take bribes, yet the ſervant will; The Proverb is commonly too <hi>true, like ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, like man.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>fourth thing,</hi> that Jeſus Chriſt did obſerve in doing his worke, was this, <hi>that he did neglect to opportunity of doing it,</hi> but did alwayes take hold up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every opportunity. When any people came together, preſently, he fell to teach them; you ſhould never have him idle.<note place="margin">Math. 5.1. Mat. 4.23, 34, 25. Mat. 9.35, 36. Mat. 13 2, 3. Luke 8.4, &amp; 5.1. &amp; 12.1. Act. 10.38.</note> But as it is ſaid in the 10. of the <hi>Acts, he went about alwayes doing good.</hi> You ſhould be like Chriſt in this alſo, obſerving every opportunity. It may be, you looſing, and neglect<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an opportunity, may looſe your hearts to do the worke. If a man be a <hi>Parliament-man,</hi> he ſhould not looſe one day of being there, to ſee what may be done for Gods glory. And if a man be a <hi>Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate</hi> of the City; he ſhould obſerve all opportuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of glorifying God; as <hi>Chriſt</hi> did. In the 7.<note place="margin">John 7.6.</note> of <hi>Iohn,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>your time is already, but my time is not come.</hi> He did obſerve, what was the beſt <hi>time,</hi> and ſeaſon to doe every thing in, this is the <hi>fourth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:117698:30"/>
Then fifthly, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt did doe his worke in his Fathers ſtrength,</hi> and <hi>in his fathers name</hi>
               <note n="(a)" place="margin">Joh. 5.19.43. John 6.47. Joh. 18.42.28. Joh. 12 49.50. Pſal. 22.1.10.</note> he did not goe out in his owne ſtrength, to doe the worke, but alwayes in his fathers ſtrength, As <hi>Pſal.</hi> 22.1.10. (which evidently is a Prophecy of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſpeaking thus:) <hi>Thou haſt cauſed me to truſt in thee from my mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wombe.</hi> And ſo when you goe about <hi>your work,</hi> labour to goe about it, in the <hi>ſtrength</hi> of the Lord: <hi>Be</hi>
               <note n="(b)" place="margin">Eph. 6.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſtrong</hi> (as the Apoſtle exhorts you) <hi>in the Lord, and in the power of his might.</hi> When you goe forth to judge people, doe you goe before by prayer? and ſay <hi>Lord, I am going to doe ſuch a worke thou cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt me to doe; ſhall I have thy ſpirit, and thy ſlrength, thy power, and thy might, to judge the people which thou aſkeſt me to judge,</hi> Conſider it: you have a heaven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Law and Charter, as well as an earthly to judge by; and a ſupernaturall power, as well as a natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall you want.</p>
            <p>And then the <hi>ſixt</hi> is this, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt</hi> he <hi>did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny himſelfe in the worke that he did doe,</hi>
               <note n="(c)" place="margin">John 8.5. &amp; 7.18.</note> 
               <hi>I ſeek not</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>my owne glory, but the glory of him that ſent me:</hi> you are to deny your own glory, yea note that; <hi>to deny your owne glory, is glory, as to ſeek your owne glory is not glory;</hi> that is a bleſſed word, <hi>he</hi>
               <note n="(d)" place="margin">1 Cor. 1.31.</note> 
               <hi>that glories let him glory in the Lord;</hi> It is better a man ſhould not doe a good worke, (for himſelfe I mean) then that he ſhould doe a good worke, and take the glory of it to himſelfe. The <hi>Angels</hi> wee finde in<note n="(e)" place="margin">Iſa. 6.2. Ezek. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and <hi>Ezekiel,</hi> they did <hi>cover their faces,</hi> their feet, and their body; why their faces? becauſe they would not ſee their owne <hi>beauty</hi> and <hi>excellency,</hi> (which is ſeene in the face) their feet becauſe they would not ſee their owne Actions. That
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117698:30"/>That is a precious ſaying, in the 15. of the firſt of the <hi>Corinths,</hi> the 10. where the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>by the grace of God I am what I am,</hi> Here he takes not to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the honour, but he gives it unto God.<note place="margin">1 Cor. 15.10.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And then ſeventhly, and laſtly, <hi>Ieſus Chriſt his laſt workes were his greateſt workes;</hi> he went on ſtill in greater works: he begun as a childe, but as he grew in ſtature, ſo his workes were greater; you that are <hi>great and Ancient Senators,</hi> that have had a long time to ſtudy the <hi>Lawes,</hi> now you ſhould act more, and appeare more for <hi>God.</hi> Now you are ready to goe to your graves, what good works will you leave behind you, that you may be had in remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance? what will your children ſay, <hi>our fathers were in a good time, when they might have glorifyed God, but they did not;</hi> Children will be ready to blame (I wiſh they may not be ready alſo to curſe) their fathers, that they did not better then they did. God hath put an opportunity now in your hands, improve it to glorifie God; and let your latter workes be bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then your former; Oh that is an honourable thing.</p>
            <p>Queſt. <hi>But it may be you will aske me, What works in particular doe you thinke we ſhould doe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw,</hi> Though it be beſt knowne to God, and better knowne to you then to me; and my worke is to ſtudy the Goſpell, rather then Law; and to ſtudy my <hi>owne</hi> worke, then to teach <hi>you</hi> what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to your offices; yet give me leave, humbly to propound three, or foure <hi>things,</hi> and ſo I will conclude.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>One</hi> maine work that Chriſt did, was to worke <hi>Reconciliation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:117698:31"/>
And this is one maine <hi>worke</hi> I would humbly deſire you to take in hand, to ſee whether you can worke <hi>reconciliation</hi> amongſt Gods people; You may remember when <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaw an <hi>Iſraelite</hi> and an <hi>Egyptian</hi> fighting together,<note place="margin">Act. 7.24.26. Exod. 2.11.13.</note> he tooke part with the <hi>Iſraelite,</hi> and ſlew the <hi>Egyptian:</hi> but when he ſaw two <hi>Iſraelites</hi> fighting together, he ſaith, <hi>where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſmiteſt thou thy fellow?</hi> He takes not part with the one againſt the other, as before, but labours to <hi>reconcile</hi> them.</p>
            <p>In the ſame way walke yee, labour to <hi>recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cile</hi> thoſe that are at variance now, <hi>eſpecially bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren.</hi> Oh! what a ſad thing is it to ſee brethren ſcratching the faces one of another? <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, that <hi>contention amongſt brethren, it like the barres of a Caſtle;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Prov. 18, 19.</note> ſtronger then other contentions. Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence amongſt brethren, of all differences, is the <hi>hardeſt</hi> difference to be reconciled; and yet it is that, which we ſhould endeavour to doe. Give me leave to offer this to you. There is now in the Nation ſome difference between Godly perſons of the <hi>Presbytery,</hi> and <hi>Independency</hi> (as they are calld,) and ſome of <hi>other</hi> opinions.</p>
            <p>Shall I intreat you from the Lord, to doe what you can to <hi>reconcile</hi> the differences between them. And, if you finde any men that are <hi>irreconcileable</hi> in their mindes, then as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> commands, <hi>Note thoſe that</hi>
               <note n="†" place="margin">Rom. 16.17.</note> 
               <hi>cauſe diviſions;</hi> But if you finde men that are reconcileable, and willing to be reconciled; endeavour then to cloſe them together in affection, and communion, I beſeech you try the worke.</p>
            <p>Obj. <hi>But Sir, it is ſuch a difficult worke, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſsible to a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e it: for many wayes have been aſſayed, and
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117698:31"/>it could never be done, what wayes would you offer now to doe it?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> There are <hi>two maine things,</hi> (or cauſes) if they were removed, the buſineſſe were ſoone ended. The <hi>one</hi> is, that they would lay aſide thoſe <hi>rigid Principles</hi> (you may call them dividing and diſuniting Principles) or ſeting up <hi>more inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> then the Lord hath ſet up.</p>
            <p>As for inſtance, to begin with the <hi>Independents,</hi> they hold ſuch a Principle as this, (which I think to be too <hi>rigid</hi>) <hi>that a man muſt be of their Church, or of ſuch a Society, as theirs is, or elſe he is not to have fellowſhip and communion with them, in the Lords Supper, though he be a Saint.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Peradventure ſome hold this, (but they are not all of this opinion.) This is too <hi>rigid</hi> a Principle, for doubtleſſe, <hi>Communion</hi> is grounded upon <hi>union;</hi> and if ſuch a man hath <hi>union with the Lord,</hi> he hath right to have<note n="†" place="margin">1 John 1.3. Rom. 14.1, 2, 3. Acts 15 8, 9. Acts 9.26, 27. 1 Cor. 1, 2, 9, 10. ch. 11. 18. 8. ch. 14. 23.</note> 
               <hi>Communion with the Saints.</hi> Then for the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> they have this opinion, that there is, and muſt be a <hi>Clasſicall,</hi> a <hi>Provinciall,</hi> and a <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Aſſembly:</hi> and all theſe <hi>jure Divino,</hi> though the word of <hi>God</hi> never hath ſuch <hi>Names,</hi> nor <hi>things.</hi> And this is to ſet up <hi>New Inſtitutions;</hi> and things which the Lord hath not ordained; Now if men would lay downe theſe <hi>rigid</hi> Principles, that are not of God, the buſineſſe might quickly be healed.</p>
            <p>The <hi>ſecond</hi> is this; <hi>Let all of them practiſe their owne principles.</hi> Mark this, The difference between <hi>Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bytery</hi> and <hi>Independency,</hi> is not ſo great in the <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> (though they differ in ſeverall <hi>Circumſtantialls</hi>) as it is in their <hi>practiſe.</hi> As the Presbyterians, one of their <hi>principles</hi> is this, <hi>that the people</hi> (or the Church)
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:117698:32"/>
               <hi>ſhould chooſe their owne MINISTER:</hi> well, let them practice that, and not urge (or import) a Miniſter upon a people.</p>
            <p>Another of their <hi>principles</hi> is this, <hi>That no perſons ſhould be admitted to the Lords Supper, that are either ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalous or ignorant.</hi> Let them practice this; and ſo they come in, and cloſe with the <hi>Independents.</hi> I might inſtance in many more, as alſo in other means (eſpecialy that each give allowance to one another: But I humbly deſire of God, and deſire of you, that you would ſee whether you can <hi>reconcile</hi> theſe diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, for the caſe of the Nation requires it, which to me ſtands thus: As a <hi>Ship</hi> that hath been in a long ſtorme, and thereby weather-beaten, and much broken; being come under the winde, and at An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chor: the Maſter of the ſhippe is conſidering what courſe to take to mend this <hi>Ship,</hi> and to make it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine navigable: But ſome in the ſhip having <hi>Commo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dities</hi> and <hi>Prizes</hi> which they are affraid ſhould be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken from them, they would, out of ſelfe-love, or diſcontent to the Maſter of the <hi>ſhippe,</hi> hoiſt up ſails, and take in more wind, and rather returne into the main ſea againe, and thereby endanger themſelves and it) the ſhippe, then wait with patience, or be croſs'd in their wills.</p>
            <p>Is it not ſo with this Nation (or Common-wealth) that hath beene ſeven yeares in the <hi>ſtorme?</hi> and God being pleaſed to bring us now under the <hi>winde,</hi> and to faſten us by the anchor of hope; And our Governours (the <hi>Maſter</hi> of the ſhippe) thinking of reforming things, ſome that are diſcontented (I name none) would rather have another people to come in, &amp; to drive it into the maine Sea of danger
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:117698:32"/>(<hi>i. e.</hi> warre) to breake it into pieces againe. Oh that this were not ſo! but oh! that thoughts of reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation might be wrought, and that if any be <hi>irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliable</hi> in their <hi>principles</hi> or <hi>practices,</hi> ſuch men were obſerved, that ſo the ſaddle might be ſet on the right horſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> In the <hi>ſecond</hi> place conſider <hi>how to relieve,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Secondly.</note> 
               <hi>and how to refreſh the poore.</hi> There were two ſorts of poor people that Chriſt relieved, ſpirituall poore, and worldly poore: To ſpeake of the laſt of theſe, which are two-fold. 1. poore <hi>priſeners;</hi> you know he came <hi>to ſet ſuch at liberty,</hi> in the 4. of <hi>Luke,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Luke 4.18.</hi> By poor here, is meant ſpecially ſpirituall priſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners.</note> v. 18. will you conſider thoſe many <hi>poor priſoners</hi> that now peradventure are for ſmall debts, made incapable of doing any ſervice to God or men; what a miſery is it to be kept in a priſon, where they cannot come to any Ordinances of God, and where they grow idle, and doe no worke, and ſo are unſerviceable to God and men. I know there is a courſe begun to relieve them, but I am affraid the <hi>plai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>r</hi> is not large enough for the ſore. Oh that theſe p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r priſoners might be ſet in ſome way whereby they might ſanctifie Gods name, and ſeeke the good of their ſoules, and not be eſtranged from God; and men. 2. There were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers Chriſt did ſupply, and they were poor <hi>beggars;</hi> we read of ſome that did beg at the Temple gates, and in the ſtreets, whom <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> did commiſerate. Now as God would not have you mercileſſe to the poore, ſo hee would not have his name abuſed by them; for the preventing of both, it's meet, you ſhould take ſome courſe of removing and taking away this begging, doubtleſſe God is much blaſphemed, and diſhonoured (and the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth</hi>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:117698:33"/>much diſgraced thereby.) What a ſhame is it, that upon the Lords day, ſo many (and it may be counterfeits) ſhould be crying in your ſtreets? <hi>for Gods ſake, for Chriſts ſake;</hi> yea doe this upon their knees, yea a hundred times, taking Gods name in vaine. <hi>There ſhould be no beggar in Iſrael,</hi> and in wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>govern'd Common-wealths there are not. And for want of better order, thoſe that would ſhew their charity, know not how to ſhew it rightly.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Thirdly.</note> And then the third thing is this; <hi>Labour to execute juſtice righteouſly and impartially.</hi> Judge the cauſe of the poore as well as of the rich, and as Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice is pictured blind, ſo be you as it were blind (I mean not ignorant, but impartiall) in executing Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice: Give to euery man, &amp; do for every man that which is juſt,<note place="margin">Ezek. 35.9.</note> and remember that word in <hi>Ezek.</hi> 45.9. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord God, let it ſuffice you O Princes of Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, remove violence and ſpoil, and execute judgement and juſtice, take away your exactions from my people ſaith the Lord God.</hi> If there be any exactions (as I fear there ſtil be) upon the people, do what you can to remove them.</p>
            <p>And then fourthly,<note place="margin">Fourthly.</note> 
               <hi>give encouragement to thoſe that are good</hi> and godly, I know not well how farre the <hi>Authority</hi> and <hi>power</hi> of civill Magiſtrates doth extend, in matters purely ſpirituall; but you the <hi>Honourable Magiſtrates of this City,</hi> I beſeech you, further good and godly people in theſe dayes, that they may have liberty to ſerve God. There are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny would come into publique, which now are in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate, if they might have liberty: And why not? for if their ware be good, why ſhould it not come into publique (as well as other mens) that it might be vended? and if it be bad and falſe, why ſhould it
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:117698:33"/>not come into publique, that it may be knowne, diſcovered, deteſted, and ſuppreſſed? why ſhould ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt people be coopt up in privat houſes, when as peradventure 20 or 30. places in this City are ſhut up, and yet they may not enjoy them; I ſpeak for them, and for Saints, that hould the head Chriſt, (I ſpeak not for them that are for toleration of corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, (or damnable opinions) but for them that walk according to the Goſpell and hold fundamentalls.</p>
            <p>And laſtly, I beſeech you,<note place="margin">Fiſthly.</note> labour to ſuppreſſe vice more; for its to be doubted, as heretofore, liberty of Conſcience, was too much denyed: ſo now, liberty to corruption is too much tolerated: For men come &amp; ſet up new ſtages on theſe days &amp; think that all this freedome is to be enjoyed for their luſts, that they may have liberty to commit wickedneſſe againe. Make it appeare that your <hi>peace,</hi> and <hi>liberty,</hi> for is not deſired <hi>carnall liberty,</hi> and for the <hi>advancement of ſin,</hi> but for the <hi>advancement of God ineſſe.</hi> There are ſome people that curſe and ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ar (the like I think, were never heard of before) publiquely in the Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, inſtead of preaching, which <hi>Doctrine,</hi> may be called the Doctrine of Divels; Others alſo that meet to whore, and drink, game and ſport, theſe things ſhould be ſuppreſt, God hath given the ſword into your hands, beſure you exerciſe it againſt the evill, and for the good, for your place is to be <hi>for terrour to evill works, and for the praiſe of thoſe that do well.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 13.3.4.</note> And ſo I conclude with that word, in the 6th. of <hi>Geneſis,</hi> (I beſeech you note it:) for I recommend it as a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall example to you the chiefe Magiſtrate of this City, in particular.<note place="margin">Gen. 6</note>
            </p>
            <p>The Text ſaith when <hi>Noah</hi> was borne, his name
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:117698:34"/>was called by <hi>Lamech, Noah;</hi> which ſignifies reſt, and why ſo? Becauſe ſaith he <hi>this ſame ſhall comfort us, (or give us reſt becauſe) of our labour and toyle, becauſe of the ground that the Lord hah curſed:</hi> Oh! that the Lord would make you a <hi>Reſt</hi> &amp; comfort to the people of this <hi>City</hi> &amp; Commonweale; your Predeceſſors have done well, do you follow them, yea excell them if you can; they have rould the ſtone farre, do you roule it further. Alſo you that are come into other mens places, as Mr. <hi>Recorder,</hi> you have the <hi>failings</hi> and the falls of other men, before you, be therefore wiſe, and watchfull, many eyes are upon you (but eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally the eyes of the Godly) &amp; ſo deſiring you to bear with my plaine and particular ſpeaking, (for it is out of true reſpect &amp; love to your Honours) I will leave this word with you, hoping that the Lord will direct you, to make a right uſe of it, to his praiſe and glory.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THis Sermon being copied out of ſhort hand, and my not being able to attend the Preſſe, hath cauſed many miſpointings and literall faults, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides ſeverall greater faults. As ſome words miſtaken, for example. <hi>Inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive</hi> for <hi>Incentive.</hi> page 32. l. 16. <hi>together</hi> for <hi>each other.</hi> p. 20. l. 20. &amp;c. So ſome words left out, as page 10. l. 5. ſo <hi>conſent,</hi> p. 18. l. 8. Likewiſe ſome words that alter the very ſenſe, as p. 23. l. 17, 18, 19. <hi>Pſalm</hi> 19.12. Who can underſtand his <hi>errours.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:117698:34"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
